<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An advertisement or admonition, unto the congregations, vvhich men call the new fryelers in the lowe Countries, wrirten [sic] in Dutche. And publiched in Englis. VVherein is handled 4. principall pointes of religion. 1. That Christ tooke his flesh of Marie, haveing a true earthly, naturall bodie, 2. That a Sabbath or day of rest, is to be kept holy everie first day of the weeke. 3. That ther is no succession, nor privilege to persons in the holie thinges. 4. That magistracie, being an holy ordinance of God, debarreth not anie from being of the Church of Christ. After these followes certen demandes concerning Gods decree of salvation and condemnation.</title>
            <author>Helwys, Thomas, 1550?-1616?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116912</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852127</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17434</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17434)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1381:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An advertisement or admonition, unto the congregations, vvhich men call the new fryelers in the lowe Countries, wrirten [sic] in Dutche. And publiched in Englis. VVherein is handled 4. principall pointes of religion. 1. That Christ tooke his flesh of Marie, haveing a true earthly, naturall bodie, 2. That a Sabbath or day of rest, is to be kept holy everie first day of the weeke. 3. That ther is no succession, nor privilege to persons in the holie thinges. 4. That magistracie, being an holy ordinance of God, debarreth not anie from being of the Church of Christ. After these followes certen demandes concerning Gods decree of salvation and condemnation.</title>
                  <author>Helwys, Thomas, 1550?-1616?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3-93, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Tho. Helvvys.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement or admonition, unto the Congregations, vvhich men call the New Fryelers, in the lowe Countries. written in Dutche.</p>
            <p>And Publiched in Englis.</p>
            <p>VVherein is handled 4. Principall pointes of Religion.</p>
            <p>1. That Chriſt tooke his Fleſh of Marie, haveing a true earthly, naturall bodie.</p>
            <p>2. That a Sabbath or day of reſt, is to be kept holy everie Firſt day of the weeke.</p>
            <p>3. That ther is no Succeſſion, nor privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to perſons in the holie thinges.</p>
            <p>4. That Magiſtracie, being an holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, debarreth not anie from being of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>After theſe followes certen demandes concerning Gods decree of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and condemnation.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pro. 9.8.</bibl>
               <p>Rebuke the wyſe, and they will love thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pro. 29.1.</bibl>
               <p>They that harden their neck, vvhen they are rebuked ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed and cannot be cured</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:2"/>
            <head>To Hans de Ries, Reynier VVy-Brantſon, and the Congregations where of they are.</head>
            <p>HAveing long deſired to publiſh our Faith vnto this nation and in perticuler vnto thoſe congregations wherof you are, (as wee have formerly done to our owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion): and alſo to make knowne the thinges wherein you, and wee differ, and are oppoſite. VVee have now through the mercie of God, thus farr, brought our deſires to paſſe, being onely vnſatiſfied for our owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency that wee are no better able to manifeſt your errors unto you wee have divers cauſes from good grounds to do this wee have done. Firſt becauſe we are bound to diſcover the miſterie of iniquitie, by all good meanes that wee can and in the cupp that ſhe hath fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to vs, to fill hir the duble. Secondly that wee might through the grace of God (if your willing minds be thereunto) be inſtrumentes of good, vnto you herein &amp; the rather, becauſe you haue bene inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of good in diſcovering divers of our erors unto us, which wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg to the praiſe of God, &amp; with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k full harts to you. Now in that wee do this by way of oppoſition and reproofe publiquely, wch you did by inſtruction priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely: for our defence herein, wee anſwere: you came publiquely amongſt us, and advanced your error of Succeſſion and order, From the proportion of the ſcriptures, and have deſtroyed the faith of manie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bye, who for ſiniſter reſpect were willinge to followe you: wee have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltt divers times with divers of yoe privately, but you have lightly regarded our loveing admonitions eſteeming all as nothinge wee have faced: ſome of you goeing on in your ſinne ſeeking to make this people one with you, who are iuſtly cutt of From God and his people for their falling avvay from Grace. VVe have writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> privately to the vvhole congregation
<pb facs="tcp:17434:3"/> you are of, to prevent you in that evill. vvee have vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten particulerly unto you H. de R. but all is in vaine, in that you eſteeme the truth vvee profeſſe, and us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as vaine. Thus are wee conſtrained (for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the truth of God wee profeſſe and that vvee may not ſeeme to juſtifie you in your evills, and to make it knovvne unto all that vvee have good cauſe to differ From you) to publiſh theſe thinges in this manner as vvee do: and that it may appeare vnto all, and to your conſciences that vvee have ſtronge grounds for ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thinges vvherein vvee differ From you, though vvee be vveake to the mainteynance of them. If anie ſhal oppoſe part or all of that is Heere vvritten, vvee d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e this equal kindnes, that it may be ſet over into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſh For all our underſtandings, as vvee have cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be ſet over into dutch for all yours, and if there becauſe of Replye, vvee vvill by the aſſiſtance of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were, vvithall the abilyty vvherevvith God ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke us able. Fare you vvell. Peace and love, vvith Faith. From God, and From our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, be with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m that are in Chriſt Ieſus, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Helvvys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17434:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Holie vvriter Iohn in the ſecond of the Revelation, vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge to the Church of Pargamus one of the Seaven Churches in Aſia, vvriteth thus verſ. 14. I have a fevv thinges aganiſt thee, becauſe thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aiſt them there that mainteyne the doctrine of Baalam, and Verſ. 15. Even ſoo haiſt thou alſo, them that maintayne the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Nicholaitanes, vvhich thinge I hate. And vvriting to the Church of Thyatira ver. 20. he ſaith. I have a fevv thinges againſt thee, that thou ſuffereſt the woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ieſabell: In all vvch, the holy man of God teacheth this that it is great impietie for anie Church of Chriſt to ſuffer anie falſe Teachers, or anie Falſe doctrine to be mainteyned by anie that are amongſt them: and if they do and repent not, the lord that hats wickednes aſmuch now as ever, vvill certenly come againſt them vvith the ſame iudgments there threatned in his vvord. And there fore wee in love fore-warne you, that profeſſe your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to be the Church of Chriſt, and yet have (heare us with patience) ſo manie doctrines of devills profeſſed and mainteyned amongſt you that you repent, leaſt the Lord riſe up in wrath againſt you: vvee ſpeake not by reports, but of our ovvne knovvledg, haveing heard vvith our owne eares and ſeene vvith our owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es the thinges vvhereof vvee ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance ſpeake.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17434:4"/>
               <head>Of Chriſts Fleſh.</head>
               <p>The Firſt matter wee will ſpeake to you is, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein your iniquitie doth greatly abound) that you have amongſt you, that deny Chriſt to have taken Fleſh of Mary: ſome holding that he brought it from heaven, and ſome not knowing from whence hee brought it, both w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich deſtroy the Faith of Chriſt, who are ſuch as Thapoſtle 2. Pet. 2, 1. Speaketh of, which privily bring in damnable heriſies, even denying the Lord that hath bought them.</p>
               <p>To ſay ſomethinge to the Firſt that hold that he brought it from heaven, that the groſſnes of their black error may appeare. The ground of ſcriptures teſtifie that that which is from heaven is heavenly, therefore if Chriſt brought his Fleſh from heaven, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he muſt have had a heavenly body, in that there can come nothinge from heaven, but that which is heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Thapoſtle 1. Cor. 15. ſaith of heavenly bodyes: They are glorious, they are not weake but of power, they are ſpirituall, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mortall. Now in that Chriſts bodie was mortall and died, it was not a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, glorious, ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituall, powerfull bodie: but was an earthly, naturall weake body, and had the ſame infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that our bodies have (ſinne excepted, as is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed Heb. 4.15. For wee have not an high Prieſt that cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but was in all thinges tempted in like ſort, yet without ſinne as alſo Chap. 5.2. which is able ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to have compaſſion on them that are ignorant, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that are out of the way, becauſe that he alſo is compaſſed with infirmitie. And his infirmities ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in that he was hungrie Mat. 4 2. He was weary Ioh. 4.6. He was trobled, and his ſoule was in great heavin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 14.33.34. And he confeſteth his Fleſh is weake. Mat. 26.41. All theſe infirmieties, nor anie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17434:4"/> infirmitie could not come from heaven, for in heaven there is no imperfection not imperfect thinge. And wee demaunde can heavenly bodies be weary? can they be hungrie? can they be trobled, and their ſoules be in heavines? or are they weake and mortall? then is there miſerie in heaven, which cannot be. Therefore it is to be concluded, never to be denyed, by anie that have Grace, that Chriſt brought not his Fleſh from heaven, in that there was infirmitie and weakenes (which is imperfection) in his Fleſh. And heere) have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo fitt occaſion) let us pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a word by the way, to them, in whoſe ſinne death &amp; hell hath conſented, which ſay that God was turned into, or made Fleſh. How could God be made weake Fleſh? whch was full of infirmities, as hath bene ſhewed by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Chriſts Fleſh was. And whereas ſome of theſe ſay, that all that Chriſt ſuffered and did in the Fleſh was but in ſhewe, it ſhalbe unto them according to their faith, if they repent not, for they ſhall have a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour but in ſhewe and though the wilfull perverſe ſtiffnes of theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe littile hope, yet let us ſay, what by the Grace of God wee are anie way able, if wee might by our beſt endeavours ſtopp men from runing ſo violently to condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ion in this accurſed iudgment that they hold, which ſay, all that Chriſt ſuffered and did heare upon earth, was but in ſhewe.</p>
               <p>And for this purpoſe wee will commend the godly diſpoſed Reader unto the xv. th. Chap. of the firſt to the Corinths, where Thappoſtle declares unto them againe, the Goſpell which he had formerly preached, and which they had received, and whereby they were ſaved, except they had beleeued in vaine. And he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that firſt of all he had delivered unto them, that Chriſt died for their ſinnes, and that he was buried, &amp; roſe again the third day. So wee preach, ad ſo have you beleved ſaith Thapoſtl not with ſtanding a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l this, ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17434:5"/> Corinthians were fallen to ſay that there was no reſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection of the dead, with whome Thappoſtle (becauſe he knewe that they had recevid and beleeved that Chriſt died and was raiſed againe) reaſoneth thus: If there be no reſurrection of the dead then is Chrſt not riſen, and if Chriſt be not riſen then is our preaching vaine, and your faith is alſo vaine, and wee are found alſo falſe witneſſes of God, for wee have teſtified of God that he hath raiſed up Chriſt, whome he hath not raiſed up, if ſo be the dead be not raiſed. Ior if the dead be not raiſed then is Chriſt not raiſed, and if Chriſt be not raiſed your faith is vaine, ye are yet in your ſinnes: and they that are a ſleepe in Chriſt are periſhed; and if in this life onely wee have hope in Chriſt, wee are of all men moſt miſerable. The Appoſtle by theſe undenyable arguments and reaſons proves Chriſts death and reſurrection: Firſt that Chriſt died ver. 3. And for profe of that, he takes the teſtimony of the ſcriptures, and by the ſame profe and warrant he proves that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was buried and roſ againe and for further confirmation of his being raiſed from the dead, Thap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle produceth the witnes and teſtimony of Cephas ſaw him and of the twelve, and he was ſeene of more then fyve hundreth brethren at once; and after of Iames: Then of all the Appoſtles, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of all of himſelf, and he addeth for further proofe hereof, their preaching, ſo wee preach ſaith Thappoſtle, and he appealeth unto their owne conſciences, for this truth of Chriſts death and reſurrection in ſaying unto them ſo have you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved.</p>
               <p>Heare Thappoſtle, that they might be brought to the ſight of the depth of the iniquitie of this their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, declares unto them, what doth neceſſarily followe if there be no reſurrection, and ſo Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt be not raiſed from the dead. And firſt concerning us ſaith Thappoſtle,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17434:5"/> (you that ſay there is no reſurrection, and ſo that Chriſt is not riſen From the dead) this followeth, you make all our preaching vaine, and ſo are wee preachers of vanie thinges, And you make us alſo falſe witneſſes of God, for wee have teſtified of God, that he hath raſed up Chriſt from the dead and this reproach do you caſt upon us. And upon your ſelves this evill do you b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in ſaing there is no reſurrection, and ſo that Chriſt is not riſen From the dead, your owne faith is in vaine, you have a vaine faith and you are yet in your ſinnes, all your ſinnes reſt upon you: further more by his your ſaying, you bring this iudgment upon all that are dead in Chriſt: that they are all periſhed and all the faith full in Chriſt that are leveing, you make them of all men moſt miſerable. And haveing thus layde before them all the evill of this there ſaying there is no reſurrection, he concludes, but now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, and was made the Firſt fruits of them that ſleepe.</p>
               <p>To turne all this evill that Thappoſtle hath Heere ſhewed unto the Corinthians (that ſaid there was no reſurrection where by it followed that Chriſt was not riſen) upon all thoſe that ſay Chriſt died but in ſhewe, and ſo died not at all in truth, it is moſt plaine that all this evill comes upon their heads, for in that they ſay Chriſt died but in ſhewe, they muſt needs ſay, he did riſe againe but in ſhewe, and ſo was there no reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in truth. And here do they (moſt miſerable men that they are all) make Thappoſtles preaching moſt vaine, for then are they preachers of vanities and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, if Chriſt be dead but in ſhewe: ſo do they make them falſe witneſſes of God, for they have teſtified of God that he raſied up Chriſt from the dead, whome he hath not raiſed up, if ſo it be he died not. Then is the faith of the faith full in vaine, and their ſinnes are yet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17434:6"/> them, if Chriſt be not dead and riſen againe, then are all that are a ſleepe in Chriſt periſhed and all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liveing are of all men moſt miſerable. But we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude againſt them all that ſay Chriſt died but in ſhew with the ſame words that the Apoſtle concludes againſt the Corinthians. But now Chriſt died, and is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againe from the dead, and was made the firſt fruts of them that ſlept. And therefore Thappoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges are not vaine, neither are they falſe witneſſes of God. And the faith of the faithfull is not in vaine, neither are any parte of there ſinnes abidinge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning yet vpon them And the faithfull that are a ſleepe are not periſhed; neither are the faithfull in this life of all men moſt miſerable. But all this is their portion that ſay Chriſt died but in ſhewe (which is not at all) their preaching is vaine, and they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achers of moſt vaine thinges. And they are falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of God, in that they teſtifie that Chriſt died not, and ſo that God raiſed him not vp from the dead, their faith is vaine, and they are yet in their ſinnes, and all that are dead in this their falſe faith are periſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed: and thus are their eſtates herein moſt miſerable.</p>
               <p>VVhat were ſufficient to ſpeake againſt this wicked blaſphemous opinion of theirs, which ſay Chriſt, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and death were but in ſhewe, theſe are they that in the higheſt degree deny Chriſt to be come in the Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h: or if they did confeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and beleeve that Chriſt were come in the Fleſh, then muſt they of force confeſſe that he died, for all Fleſh muſt needs dye and be changed as is ſhewed Iſa. 10.6. and 1. Pet 1.24 All Fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory thereof is as the Flower of the Feild. And all the glory of man is as the Flower of graſſe which withereth and Falleth away. All the diſciples of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt never made queſtion of his death for they ſaw and were ſore he was dead, and therefore they began to doubt of his reſurrection
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17434:6"/> through infidelitie, which there had bene no cullor for them to doubt of, if they had bene of theſe mens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that he died but in ſhewe.</p>
               <p>In that all that is ſpoken of the reſurrection from the dead, is ſpoken of Chriſt, it ſhall not be amiſſe yet further to conſider what the holy ghoſt by the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſheweth in this 1. Cor. 15. Chap. concerning the reſurrection from the dead, for by his reſurrection his death ſhall appeare. This is that then which Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtl hath ſett downe heare concerninge Chriſts death and reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and concerning his naturall and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodie, and his ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituall and heavenly body, Thap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth ſhewe firſt of all in the 3. Verſ. That Chriſt died, and Verſ. 20. Now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, and Verſ. 35. there is a queſtion how the dead are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up: to which queſtion the Appoſtle annſweres, ſpeaking of all dead bodies in generall, and of Chriſts dead bodie in particuler (whome he hath ſhewed in the 20. Verſ. to be the firſt friuts of them that ſleepe) That which thou ſoweſt (ſaith Thappoſtle) is not qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned except it dye, teaching hereby as he had ſhewed before that Chriſts body did dye, and all bodies muſt dye firſt, or els they cannot be quickned, that is, raiſed againe from the dead verſ. 36. Then it being moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in this ſcripture proved. That Chriſt was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead, it is as evidently heere proved that he muſt needs, and did firſt dye: for (ſaith Thappoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) it could not be quickned except it firſt dye. And Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtl haveing thus annſwered to that part of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, in ſheweing how the dead are raiſed, then he proceeds to the ſecond queſtion, whch is, with what bodies come they furth, to which queſtione hee anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wereth Verſ. 37.38. Thou ſoweſt not that body that ſhalbe, but God giveth it a body at his pleaſure, to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeed his owne body. Heere Thapoſtle ſheweth, that Chr. body, &amp; all bodyes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t are of Chr. (for of thoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17434:7"/> onely doth he ſpeake as appeareth verſ. 23.) are not rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the reſurrection with thoſe bare bodies that are ſowen, but God giveth a bodie at his pleaſure; even to every ſeed his owne body, that is to the ſeed of man, all one body (to them which are raiſed in Chriſt) for there is but one Fleſh of men. The Apoſtle haveing Heere Firſt ſhewed, that the ſame bare body that is ſowne ſhall not ſo be raiſed up againe, then he ſheweth what manner of body it ſhalbe in the reſurrection, and wherein it ſhall differ from that wch was ſowen and died. In the 40. verſ ſaith Thappoſtle, there are heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies, and earthly bodies, and in the 49. verſ. wee ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage of the heavenly. Heere is ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with what manner of bodies the dead are raſed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fruits of the dead, with ſuch a body was he rayſed: then followeth how the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly body and the earthly body do differ in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the earthly body is corrupt, diſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>norable, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, naturall, and mortall. The heavenly body i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> incorrupt glorious, ſtronge ſpirituall, immortall. The image of the earthly body wee have from the Firſt Adam, wch was made (ſaith Thappoſtle) a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſoule, that is, naturall and earthly. The ymage of the heavenly body all that are of Chriſt ſhall have from the laſt Adam a quic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſpirit, that is, ſpirituall, heavenly wch is the ymage of Chriſts glorious as body after his reſurrection. Thus wee ſee the whole d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt and intent of Thappoſtl in all this ſcripture is to prove the reſurrection from the dead, and how the dead riſe, and with what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bodies and all this by Chriſts death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, becauſe as he died and riſſe againe, in the fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> order verſ 23. with the ſame bodies verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. ſhall all that are of Chriſt uſe againe, proveing hereby alſo that Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a naturall earthly, and mortall body; ſowen in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uption, in diſhonor, and in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raiſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17434:7"/> in incorruption, in glory, in power, a ſpirituall body, Heavenly, immortall, what can be more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe, if men that have eies would ſee, and would not wincke with their eies; why will men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the ſcriptures to their owne diſtruction? takeing Heere a peece of a ſentence, and there a peece, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lookeing to the ſcope and ſence. And thus much according to our ſmale talent to ſhewe the error of them that are fallen, to ſo deepe diſtruction, as to ſay, God was turned into fleſh, and ſo his death and all his ſufferings were but in ſhewe: and to ſay them (if by the grace of God it may be) that are not fallen ſo far.</p>
               <p>And now to ſpeake to them that knowe not from whence Chriſt had his fleſh, they ſee it proved that from heaven he could not have it, for then there could not poſſibly have bene infirmitie in it. They ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or through the grace of God might ſe, that Chriſt had a naturall, earthly, mortall body, and that there is but one Fleſh of men will they ſtill remaine igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and doubting whence Chriſt had his fleſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then do they ſtill remaine in ſinne. Let them therefore leave their doubting (wch is through their ignorance) if they looke for ſalvation by Chriſt and let them knowe and beleeve from the ſcriptures of God. That Chriſt is of the ſeed of David, and of the Iſralites according to the Fleſh. Rom. 2.3. And 9.5. The Sonne of Mary the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, made of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubſtance. Gal. 4.4. And ſo doth this agree with the Firſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e made concerning Chriſt Gen. 3.15. VVhere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſpoken by God: That the ſeed of the woman ſhall breake the ſerpents head, without wch knowledg and Faith, no man ſhall ever be ſaved: ffor there is no ſalvation, but by Chriſt the promiſſed ſeed of the woman. Thoſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> you that
<pb facs="tcp:17434:8"/> will not knowe and beleeve that Chriſt is the ſeed of the woman, conceyued in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wombe, by the power of the moſt high overſhadowing hir, ſhall never be ſaved by Chriſt the promiſſed ſeed of the woman. This then is your great ſinne that you ſuffer manie amongſt you that mainteyne a falſe faith concerning where Chriſt had his Fleſh; and you approve and allowe of ſome, that hold and mainteyne no faith concerning where Chriſt had his Fleſh, and ſo do you approve and mainteyne them in their ſinne, for whatſoever anie holds or mainteynes not of ſaith is ſinne: and to be ignorant of anie part of that the ſcriptures hath manifeſted is ſinne, and to determyne to remaine ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and ſo to continewe unto the end is death for without repentance anie one ſinne is death as Thappoſtle Iames ſheweth Iam. 2.10. VVho ſoever ſhall kepe the whole law and yet faileth in one point he is giltie of all. Deceyve not ſimple ſoules then by noriuſhing them in their ſinne, which you do, in ſaying it is not needfull to ſalvation to knowe whence Chriſt had his Fleſh, as though there were anie part of the law or goſpell, not needfull to ſalvation. And if there be anie part of the law not needfull then Chriſt need not to have come to fulfill the whole law, which he did as he ſaith Mat. 5.17. And if there be anie part of the goſpel of ſalvation (which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his blood Ephe. 1.13.14.) not needfull to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then Chriſt hath purchaſed more then is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. In the feare of God walke not thus by your owne inventions, leading and ſuffering ſimple ſoules, to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in the waies of death and condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17434:8"/>
               <head>Of the day of reſt.</head>
               <p>The ſecond is, that manie among you (and how farr you are all poluted wee knowe not but have great cauſe to feare) do profeſſe &amp; practice not to kepe the ſeaventh day, a day of reſt, &amp; holy vnto the lord, aboliſhing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the law, which was given in the mount out of the midſt of the fire in the day of the aſſemblie, and which was written in the Tables with the finger of God, as is ſhewed Exod. 20.8.9.10.11. and Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10. Of all wch whole law, our ſaviour Chriſt ſaith Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5, 17.18. I am not come to diſtroy, but to fulfill: for truely I ſay vnto you, till heaven, and earth periſh, one jot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or one title of the law ſhall not ſcape till all thinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be fulfilled: not with ſtanding all the ſpoken by God the father, &amp; Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, manie of you with an high hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out, and diſtroy one of theſe Ten Commandements written by the finger of God Exod. 34.28. and you will have but Nyne, ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g a ſunder the law of God, and caſting away what is not pleaſing vnto you. Not hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the examples of the diſciples of Chriſt a ſufficient rule of direction for you, who as is ſhewed Act. 20.7 and 1. Cor. 16.1, 2. The firſt day of the weake came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to breake bread. Vpon euery vvhich firſt day of the weeke, when they were come together Paul ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Churches that every one ſhould lay aſide for the neceſſitie of the Saincts, that there might be no ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering when he came.</p>
               <p>How will you be able to ſtand before the lord here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath eſtabliſhed a law, the which it is more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie that heaven and earth ſhould paſſe away, then that one title of the law ſhould fall Iuc. 16.17. And if you now be able to ſhewe (which God forbid that anie ſhould be ſo wicked as to enterp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe) that all theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17434:9"/> words, ſpoken and written by God himſelf. Remember the Sabath day to keepe it holy, be no part, jot, nor tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this law, then you have ſome cullor for the evill you practice and profeſſe herein: but dare anie moueth of blaſphemy ſpeake it? or anie hand of blaſphemy write it? wee hope no, why then give glory to God, &amp; repent of this your ſinne, and pray the lord that if it be poſſible the thoughts of your harts, the blaſphemy of your mouethes, and the wickednes of your hands may be forgiven you. And ſinne not as you do againſt God, in turning away your feet from the Sabath of the lord, and doeing your owne wills on his holy day, wherein alſo you do wronge to man, and beaſt, to whome the lord hath in mercie given a ſpeciall day of reſt. But yet further to ſhewe you that wich you ſhall never be able to annſwere. Our Sauiour Chriſt Mat. 24.20. ſpeakeing of the diſtruction of Ieruſalem (which was to come to paſſe, &amp; did, long after his death) ſaith. Pray that your flight be not in the winter, nor on the Sabath day, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weing vndenyably, that ther ſhould ſtill remaine a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall day of reſt, for the people of God to worſhip him on: vpon which day Chriſts bidds them pray that their flight be not, that they might not be forced to flie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould reſt and worſhipp God. And if our Saviour Chriſt had ment that his diſciples ſhould have bene of your iudgment, it had bene all one, vpon what day their flight had bene. God give you grace to ſee your great error herein, that you may not ſtill be hate full to God, and men, and Beaſts. And thus much of this, except further occation be offered: Omitting to ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we you all the confuſion you bring into the Church when there ſhalbe no day certen whereon the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ought to come together, to edifie one an other, to breake bread, to pray, and to gather for the Saincts, if your rule be true (which is as falſe as God is true) they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17434:9"/> chuſe, whether they will come at all, except you have authoritie to make a law to bind them, which ſure you have not from God: even ſo do you confound hereby all due proceeding in the rule of admonition by the Church, if there be no certen day when the Church are bound to meet. But wee wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l paſſe by this, hopeing you will fall vnder the former ground, and then you will eaſily ſee (through the grace of God) all theſe thinges, and manie mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which accompanie that your error, that do vtterly deſtroy all godlines, Religion, and the holy communion of Saincts. Therefore repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake this your error, for if you do thus diſtroy the lawe of God, there can be no Religion of God in you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17434:10"/>
               <head>Of Succeſſion.</head>
               <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your Leaders are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them that mainteyne a Succeſſion, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and you will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and tongues to come to you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ordinances of Chriſt: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> adminiſter in the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power and all the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the man of ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> called o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 3.1.2.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner of way? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of credit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> proceed from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ieruſalem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> call your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> do, to your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to it, and to them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17434:10"/> everlaſting diſtruction in ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing and ſuffering them ſelves to be to dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Thus then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeake of the heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vp to the mountaine of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner ſpeaketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd ſhall ſend the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Prophecies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> taught the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when he ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> word of the lord our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you alſo taught of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> humbled, and humble your ſelve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>If this will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prophet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Compact together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Tithes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to praiſe the name of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> but the Tithes muſt come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the grace of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> but you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalbe the people. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17434:11"/> Mount Syon, which cannot be removed? and ſhal you remaine for ever? If you can promiſſe this of your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, you go beyond all the excellent Churches that are ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the new teſtament, whereof there remaines no mention at this day to be ſeene but onely that the ſcriptures teſtify that ſuch Churches there were but not one of them hath remained vnto this day. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none of them were Mount Syon. And will you lift vp your horne on high, and be more then they all? this is the fooliſhnes of folly, beare with our rudenes: The lord knoweth wee ſeeke his glory and your good he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein, although our infirmities may too much appeare. It is your turning from theſe your evills that wee diſire, for Godes glorie and the ſalvation of your ſoules: and therefore will wee through Gods grace, endeavour yet further to ſhewe you your error in this point.</p>
               <p>The Prophet in the 48. Pſal. 2.3. Seaketh on this wiſe Mount Syon Northward is faire in ſcituation, it is the joy of the whole earth &amp; the Citie of the great king. In the Palaces thereof God is knowne for a refuge, and verſ. 8. God will eſtabliſh it for ever, Selah. To add vnto this, the glorious diſcription ſo at large ſett downe by Iohn. Reuel. 21.10. VVhere he ſaw, that great Citie that holy Ieruſalem deſcending out of heaven from God, whoſe wall had twelve foundations, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in them the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the twelve Appoſtles of the lambe verſ. 14. wch Citie hath no need of the Sunne, neither of the Moone to ſhinne in it, for the glorie of God doth light it, and the lambe is the light of it verſ. 23. And the people that are lived ſhall walke in the light of it verſ. 24. And the Nation, &amp; the kingdome that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh: and theſe nations ſhalbe vtterly diſtroyed Iſa. 60.12. See your ſelves now how unlike you are this Citie: are you the joy of the whole earth? ſorrowe is the ioy that wee the poore wineſſes of Chriſt have in you for our partes, as you ſhall further heare: do
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17434:11"/> the people that are ſaved walke in the light of you? and ſhall the nation, and kingdome that will not ſerve you periſh? God forbid: be content and glade to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve this Citie your joy, and to be Citizens of this Citie, and to walke in the light of it, and to ſerve it or els you ſhall periſh and be deſtroyed. But this Citie cannot periſh nor be deſtroyed, but you may be, and therefore you are not this Ieruſalem: and the world knowes that you are not the earthly Ieruſalem, wincke not with your eies but ſee, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pp not your eares but heare how the word of God doth convince you in this your error.</p>
               <p>And now wee beſeech the vpright harted amongſt you to be willing to heare what Thappoſtle Paule doth ſhewe Ieruſalem to be, and followe not your owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions herein. Th'appoſtle to the Gal. 4.22-26. ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that Abraham had two ſonnes, and two wives, one ſonne by a ſervant, and one by a free woman, he wch was borne of the ſervant was borne after the fleſh, and he that was of the freewoman was borne by promiſſe. By the which thinges, another thinge is ment (ſaith Th'appoſtle) for theſe mothers are the two teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, The one which is Hagar or Syna is a mountaine in Arabia, and it aunſwereth to Ieruſalem which now is, and ſhe is in bondage with hir children. But Ieruſalem which is above, is free which is the mother of us all. Thus doth Th'appoſtle ſo plainely as is poſſible (for the vnderſtanding of all) teach, that by Hagar the bond wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is mente the old Ieruſalem which is the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with all the carnal ordinances there of. And by Sarah the free woman, is ment the new Ieruſa. the new Teſtament, with all the ſpirituall ordinances thereof. And this ſpirituall mother, which is Sarah the free wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the new Ieruſalem, the new Teſtament, is mother of all that are borne after the ſpirit: and they are hir childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Th'appoſtle ſaith of himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verſ. 31
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17434:12"/> Now will you be this Ieruſalem, the mother of all the faith full? will it not ſuffice you to be children, but you muſt be the mother of all? Do but ſee how herein you agree with that Antichriſt of Rome that wil be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all Churches. How farr contrary is this to all the reſt of your profeſſion, who profeſſe ſuch humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mynd in all thinges, and yet hereyn to ſeeke thus highly to advice yours ſelves above the poore ſervants of God, that through his grace and mercie by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his word and ſpirit, are borne children of the free woman: and though weak childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet borne as free as you or anie: what great evill is this (in ſoo maine of you as would to ſeeke to bring vs in bondage vnto you when you cannot (by aine warrant of Gods word) have anie more freedome in anie holy thinge, or to anie holy thinge, then wee, if wee be all the Children of one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for then are wee brethren. Synne not thus againſt God, and wronge not vs, by ſeeking to tread vs vnder your feet, which you do, in advanceing your ſelves over vs to bring vs in ſubiection, who are borne as free as you.</p>
               <p>This being by the word of God made cleare that neither you, nor anie Church, congregation, or people, are Ieruſalem, it will eaſily follow, that nether you nor anie Church congregation or people are the kingdome of heaven for the heavenly Ieruſalem, and the kingdome of heaven are all one, as all that have anie vnderſtanding agree and knowe. Therefore it ſhall not be needfull to vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds mo in this cauſe, lett vs inſhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewe what the ſcriptures ſpeaketh of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven. Our Saviour Chriſt Luc. 4.34. Saith thus. Surely I muſt alſo preach the kingdome of God to other Cities for therefore am I ſent. This kingdome cannot in anie vnderſtandinge be ment of anie people, for it muſt be preached to a people and this agrees with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17434:12"/> that before ſpoken of Ieruſalem which is, that it is the new Teſtament. And thus ſpeaketh our Saviour Chriſt Ioh. 3.5. except a man be borne of water and of the ſpirit, he cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into the kingdome of God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby it is ſo plaine as anie thinge can be that no people are the kingdome of God, but that people ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of God, and when they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, then are of the kingdome of God and children of the kingdome Mat. 13.38. And therefore wee pray the Godly reader to conſider, that there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twix the kingdome, and the people otherwiſe where was the kingdom before your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irſt begininge? was there no kingdome, for your firſt beginners to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? did they make a kingdome and enter into it and all of themſelves? then ſure it was not the kingdome of God, and it ſtands you vpon to looke it be for if they ſet vp a new kingdome, they entred not into Chriſts kingdome, for Chriſts kingdome was and is an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome, and cannot be ſhaken, as the Author to the Hebrewes ſheweth Heb. 12.22. ſpeaking of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt Syon, the Cittie of the liveing God, the Celeſtiall Ieruſalem Verſ. 28. Seeing wee receive a kingdome that cannot be ſhaken, let vs have grace, whereby wee may ſo ſerve God, that wee may pleaſe him with reverence and feare.</p>
               <p>VVee have endeavoured with our beſt abilities (wch you may ſee are ſmale) to ſpeake the larger of this point becauſe wee our ſelves have bene formerly miſledd with this error, that the Church is the kingdome of heaven, and monut Syon, and becauſe wee knowe ſome others are ſtrongly poſſeſſed therewith, which not with ſtanding hold not Succeſſion, but indeed it is the ground of all Succeſſion for if the Church be Ieruſalem, then muſt there needs be Succeſſion, for there muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> needs be adue proportion of all thinges betwene the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17434:13"/> Tipe &amp; the truth, betwene the old Ieru: &amp; the new Ieru: betwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the ſhadow &amp; the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And there being therfore Succeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, there muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be Succeſsion in the new. If therefore you can prove your ſelves Ieruſalem, wee yeild you all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of Ieruſalem. Then muſt all people &amp; nations come to you, and receive all the holy ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces from you. Then muſt all ſacrifices be offered vp in you. And then they that are not in you, are not in Chriſt. And all that are borne of water &amp; of the ſpirit, muſt enter into you, and all that are ſaved muſt walke in the light of you. And then are you the ioy of the whole earth. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt you be perached to other Cities, and then can you not be ſhaken, for Chriſtes kingdome is an everlaſting Kingdome, which ſhall never be taken away nor be deſtroyed Dan. 7.14. But you may be ſhaken, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and deſtroyed though you were as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celent a Church as Corinth. Epheſus, Phillippi, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſa: Smyrna, Philadelphia, for all they are ſhaken, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, &amp; deſtroyed, which were much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Churches then you, euen ſo may you much more be. Therefore you are not the kingdome of heaven: nor that heavenly Ieruſalem, and ſo thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges belong not to you, which you challenge, and ſome wretched men have given you (whoſe condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſleepeth not) and all vnder that culler of your being Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>And let vs now bring to trial your other ground con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this cauſe, which is. That the ordinances of Chriſt being (as you call it) once raiſed vp againe they are not to be raiſed anie more, but all men muſt fetch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from thoſe that raiſed them vp, or from them that have received them at their handes by Succeſſion Firſt wee ſay vnto you that, which ſome of you could not.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17434:13"/> nor you all ſhall ever be able to annſwere whilſt the world endureth.</p>
               <p>How knowe you of faith, that he or they from who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me you received your begininges were the firſt? This can you never prove to anie mans conſcience that hath anie conſcience, except you can ſhewe Prophecie of ſcripture perticulerly that ſuch a man ſhould firſt raiſe up (to ſpeake your owne vvord) the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of Chriſt, and that he hath done it, and that you haue it from him: All theſe muſt you prove by ſcripture, if your rule be true, and that men muſt have faith in it: but not anie one of theſe can you prove by ſcripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd therefore your rule is not true, and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can have faith in it and then not to be hold and practiced by anie that wait for ſalvation by Ieſus Chriſt, vvho muſt have faith in all that they hold, profeſſe, &amp; practice, or els they ſinne: ffor vvithout faith it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe God. Rom. 11.6. Let us by the mercies of God intreat all you that profeſſe the name of Ieſus, not to ſtand vpon ſuch vncertaine and vnfound groundes: For wch vvay ſhall you ever be able to prove, that he or they from vvhome you (by Succeſſion) have your begining vvere the firſt? No man can ever prove it, the vvorld is too vvide for man to comprehend or knowe all that is done in it. It is avaine invention, caſt it away, ſeeing there is no vvarrant in Gods vvord to vvarrant it vnto you, that he or they vvere the firſt.</p>
               <p>And if he, or they vvere, vvhat then? Muſt all the vvorld come to them? By vvhat rule of Gods word? There muſt be a ſpeciall commaund for him, or them to beginne: And a reſtraint or forbiddinge comaund to all men for doeing the ltie after: ffor God is as mercifull to his people now as ever he vvas, and he hath not left them without rule of direction, that they ſhould ſinne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17434:14"/> and fall was the lord ſo carefull for his people Iſraell (for whome he had wrought ſo great wonders, and yet they were continually rebellious againſt him) as to give Moſes twice warning at one time Ex. 19.21. and 21. Goe downe charge the people that they breake not to the lord to gaze, leaſt manie of them periſh And againe lett not the Preiſts, and the people breake to come vpto the lord leaſt they be deſtroyed. And did the lord moſt carefully appoint Aaron and his ſonnes, their ſeverall Offices and ſervices about the Tabernacle as is ſhewed Numb. 4. where the lord chargeth Moſes and Aaron that they ſhould not cutt of the Tribe of the famili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Kohathites: But this do vnto them, ſaith the lord that they may live and not dye, let Aaron &amp; his ſonnes come and appoint them every one to his charge, leaſt they touch or ſee thoſe holy thinges, they ought not to touch and ſee, and dye, was the lord out of his great grace, mercie, and love ſo carefull for his people then, to give ſuch ſtrait rules of direction to them, leaſt they ſhould come neare, handle, or ſee thoſe thinges which apperteyned not to them to handle or ſee and ſo ſinne, and dye. And hath the lord left to beg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> now, in leaveing his people no directions, nor directors to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffice, and ſhewe them what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comaunded and what is for bidden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Surely you will not ſay, but the lord is as mercifull to rebellious Iſraell as ever he was, then wee require you to ſhew, where the lord hath now comaunded ſome eſpecially to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne and meddle with the holy thinges, and for bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den all others except by their appointment they be permittd &amp; appointed therevnto. If you will thus ſett vp a ſpeciall Temple and Preiſt hood of your owne, ſhewe your warrant from the word of truth which ſeeing poſſiblie you cannot do, let God have the glorie, and ſee your owne ſhame, and humble your ſelves, &amp;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17434:14"/> repent of this error. VVill you now with patience ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs a little to declare and try your beſt ground f<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r theſe thinges, wich wee have received from ſome that are greateſt amongſt you wee could repeat divers of your arguments and reaſons, but wee ſpare you, &amp; wee will take your ſtrongeſt ground, which if wee can by the ground of truth ſhewe to be moſt vnſound, wee will hope that they amongſt you, that ſeeke the lord in ſinglenes of hart will forſake it: firſt knowe this and let all knowe that you have never bene able at anie time, to produce anie one ſcripture and mainteyne it, for your Succeſſion, although wee have had divers confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences with the cheifeſt amongſt you but you reaſon by ſimelies and proportions of your owne deviſings for the moſt part.</p>
               <p>To come to your ground, this is the ſome of that you ſaie. That baptiſme being once raiſed vp by one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized, after, none did, neither was it lawfull for anie vnbaptized to baptize, but all muſt have it from him, &amp; ſo you follow on with your proportion from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, to the church and miniſtry. And this is the waie you runne, not knowing whether it leads jou, wee praie you marke what the wiſeman ſaith. Pro. 4.19. The wa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the vngodlie is as the darknes, they knowe not vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhall fall: even ſo little do you knovve into vvhat pitt you ſhall fall, or vpon what rock you do caſt your ſelves &amp; others in this your way firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ſay, that when baptiſme was once (by one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized raiſed vpon <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, none after being vnbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized did or might. This John never taught you, nor <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appoſtles, where els you have learned it wee know not, but you <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in it, and ſay it is the courſe &amp; order of the ſcriptures. But wee require you with godly conſideration to conſider that heerein vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of binding to the due <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> courſe of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17434:15"/> the matter &amp; manner of the ſcriptures (which all oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to follow) you bring men to a due perticuler courſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vvhich none are bound to follow except anie da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie ſay of themſelves, as that excellent &amp; vvorthy Appo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle Paul. ſaid. Phil. 2.17. Brethren, be followers of me In ſhort ſee, if you would not be blynd, vvhether you rule leades you, if you wil tye the vvord &amp; ordinance of God vnto men: Priſt for baptiſme, you muſt bring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> man prophecied of, as Iohn vvas, that ſhalle able, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> annſvvere as Iohn did to them that asked him, vvha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> art thou that vvee may giue aunſwere to them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſent us, vvhat ſaieſt thou of thy ſelf? vvhy baptize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou? Iohn aunſweres. I am hee that the Prophet Eſaia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prophecied of &amp;c. I am the voice of him that crieth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the vvildernes, make ſtraight the vvay of the lord Thus doth Io: prove his office &amp; miniſtration to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and therefore might Ieruſalem &amp; all Iudea of faith come faith to him to be baptized: And this man vvas ſent in the power of the ſpirit of Elias. Therefore vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he did in his miniſtry vvas true and vvarrantable ſo that men might ſafely joyne themſelves to his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: Neither could men learne baptiſme &amp; the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof but of Iohn, &amp; of them that received it from him, vvil you now in the behalf of your firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner, aunſwere us that aske vvho art thou that bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeſt? And ſaieſt all men muſt have their baptiſme from thee, VVhat ſaieſt thou of thy ſelf? VVhere is thy vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant? VVil you aunſwere vs as you have done, that Io: his example is your vvarrant? VVee vvil aunſwere you (as vvee have often done) wee alſo do the like by the ſame example. And wee ſay farther, that Iohns example, and al the examples &amp; rules in the ſcriptures to be followed are generall, and there is no one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler example or rule in all the new Teſtament, wch is onely to be ymmitated &amp; obſerved, by anie one man, anie two.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17434:15"/>
               <p>Tenn twenty or a hundreth: but what ſoeuer example in the ſcriptures, anie one Man may followe, and what ſoever rule or commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t anie one man may obſerve &amp; kepe, even ſo another man may followe the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample &amp; keepe the ſame coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſo of two men ten, twenty, or an hundreth. And the like may be ſaid of time, &amp; place: for there is no example or rule in the new Teſtament, that is onely proper or appirtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning to anie one perſon, or perſons time, or times, place or places for the new teſtament is the Covenant of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his blood, and there is no part of it can be aboliſhed till he come to iudgment: But if anie part of it, anie example, or rule in it be tyed to anie particuler perſon or perſons, time, or times, place or places theſe al may be aboliſhed before Chriſtes coming, and therefore no part of the new teſtament, can be particulerly tyed to anie one of them.</p>
               <p>To ſhewe for example the queſtion in hand. If Iohns example of Baptizing, being vnbaptized (or rather not being of anie other firſt baptized) If his example be a particuler exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple for one man onely (as you ſay) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <note place="bottom">jt follovveth.</note>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17434:16"/> was it aboliſhed when your predeceſſor had once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to Baptize, and ſo is that example now of no vſe, and it may be for anje thinge you knowe or ever can knowe that he was not the firſt, and then if your rule be true how wretched is your caſe, that challeng apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regative, that by your owne rule apperteynes not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and your beſt advantage is, that you can but jmagine that you are the firſt and you would have vs jmaigine ſo with you.</p>
               <p>VVell, wee beſeech you conſider throughly this one point eſpecially. That the new teſtament, nor anie part of it neither rule nor example, doth perticulerly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne to anie one perſon, or ſerve onely for anie one perſon, or ſerve onely for aine one time, or place, wch if you deny, you aboliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Teſtament purchaſed with his blood, and makes it a carnall cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for no ſpirituall covenant can eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be aboliſhed. And if you confence that the new Teſtament, and all the rules &amp; examples therein, are generall to all: Then may all men, in all places, whome the lord by his word and ſpirit ſhall ſtirr vp, and indue with gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce preach the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and men being converted, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, &amp; ſo is your Succeſſion fallen to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And therein have you no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, if you love the lord, &amp; his holy truth, for thereby ſhall the holy ordinances of Chriſt be ſett at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which you have kept in bond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, and to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> divers ſoules whoſe blood wilbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your hands (though they be periſhed in their owne ſinnes) if you repent not.</p>
               <p>Moreover as wee have ſhewed before. Iohn came in the power and ſpirit of Elias, therefore what ſoever he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> office and miniſtrie was warrantable and according to truth, and he could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> therein. This no man that knovves anie truth vvill denie, and vvee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17434:16"/> ſpeake to men of vnderſtanding. And came your firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner in the power of the ſpirit in this meaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and was all warantable and according to the truth that he did in his miniſtery? will anie affirme that all was warrantable that he did? or can anie affirme it? and that he could not err-God forbid that anie fearing God ſhould be ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: nay was he not a man coming furth in ſome ſmale meaſure of the deepe miſt of the miſtery of iniquitie, being then in much error and ignorance yea even in that adminiſtration of baptiſme orels you haue bene vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table diſciples of his. And would you tye all the world from the Eaſt to the weſt to come fetch the holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt from him, &amp; you, his ſucceſſors, through all your errors ignorances, and grevious corruptions, where of wee knowe ſo manie, and have cauſe to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of you for maine moe. VVhat truth, pietie, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines is there in this? that you ſhould ſeeke to make men either preſently ſwallowe vp all your errors ignorantly, to be waſhed of you with water, or els ſtay vntill they have learned them, otherwiſe they muſt not be baptized at all. And further that men muſt be forced to learne your language, and ſo vntill the poore diſciples of Chriſt that would followe him, (Engliſh men or aine other nation) can ſpeake dutch, they are debarred from the holy ordinances of God the meanes of their ſalvation by this your rule, a fearefull miſtery of iniquitie.</p>
               <p>Hereby you have wrought ſuch wickednes amongſt vs, and brought ſuch deſolation vpon vs the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, as wee have cauſe to wiſh that in our heades were floodes of water, and our eies were fontaines of teares, that wee might power out a complainte againſt you, for this your abhomination, wich you have ſet vp, whereby you have wrought ſuch deſtruction and ruine in the Church of God, ſeeking to pull it downe, to build vp your ſelves. Hereby have you glorified your Church, &amp; ſett hir vp to ſitt as a Queene, takeing vnto your ſelves
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17434:17"/> all power &amp; authoritie, yea even to ſhutt the gates of the holie Cittie, the heavenly Ieruſalem, ſaieing that none may enter but by your authoritie. Oh that you could ſee your great ſinne herein, &amp; the lamentable evill that you have wrought. Firſt againſt God in deſtroying his Temple, which is built truely (though exceeding weakely) vpon the foundation the word of God. And you have cauſed the enimies of God to blaſpheme, &amp; to make a mock at the profeſsion of Ieſus Chriſt. And you have cauſed them that were more indifferently mynded, to doble their doubtings, and rather ſtepp backward, then come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Thus have you ſinned with an high hand againſt the God of heaven, who is able and will fill you the duble for this your iniquitie, if you repent not. And for vs you have brought much ſorrow, greife &amp; vexation of ſoule &amp; ſpirit vpon vs. The Lord doth knowe wee ſpeake truely and great hath bene our cauſe of greife to ſee the Church of Chriſt, which is his body, whereof wee are (though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie members) thus rent and torne in pecces, and our profeſsion and wee made a ſcorne of men, who have wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed and wayted for our overthrow, and have taken vpon them to foretell, of theſe evills that have come vpon vs, which being come to paſſe according to their foretelling, they have triumphed againſt vs &amp; bleſſed themſelves, as though their foreſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eings muſt needs come to paſſe. Thus have our enimies reioyced at our miſeries, but the Lord hath wounded them vpon their right eie, and made them a reioyceing to their enimies.</p>
               <p>VVere this all our woe, it were at full, enough, but you have by this your great ſinne brought a further evill vpon vs, then to make our enimies reioyce over vs, ſaying there, there, ſo would wee have it, for you have made our frends our enimies, yea our familier frends, with whome wee tooke ſweet counſell, &amp; went together to the houſe of God. And ſuch is the enmitie betwixt vs and them
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17434:17"/> (whereof you have bene cheife inſtruments) as it can neuer have end, whilſt anie of vs live, for it is that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, which the Lord put betwene the ſeed or the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the ſeed of the ſerpent, which can have no end in them except wee fall into the ſame deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for there is no p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace to repentance to be found for their trangreſſion. For they were once enlightned, and had truſted of the heavenly gift, and were made part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of the holy ghoſt. And had taſtied of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come: and are fallen away: it is impoſſible they ſhould be renewed againe by repentance: ſeeing they crucifie againe to themſelves the ſonne of God and make a mock of him Heb. 6.4.5.6. Now to ſhewe how they were once enlightned. Firſt Mr. Iohn Smy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon whoſe head the blood of all this people ſhalbe) hath by his profeſſion in all his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and by word, and in his ſundrie writings, with ſuch force of argument, and ſtrength of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation with ground of truth, (as his writings ſhewe) manifeſted himſelf to be enlightned with this truth of God.</p>
               <p>That whereſoever two, or three, are gathered to gether into Chriſts name, there Chriſt hath promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be in the midſt of them Mat. 18.20. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are the people of god and Church of Chriſt, haveing right to Chriſt, and all his ordinances, and need not ſeeke to men to be admitted to the holie thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but may freely walke together in the waies of god, and enioy all the holie thinges. From this truth of god wherewith he was enlightned is he fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, denying the words of our Saviour Chriſt. That ſaith whereſoever two or three are gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp;c. And holdeth that the firſt two or three that are gathered togither have onely right to Chriſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17434:18"/> and all his ordinances, and that after, all men muſt come to them, reſtraning the wordes of Chriſt wch are generall ſo anie two or three, onely to the firſt two or three, and ſo hath ſett vp a Succeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the wch he hath former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by all wordes, writinges, &amp; practice ſett himſelf with all deteſtation. And this man like Balaam hath conſulted with you, and hath putt a ſtumbling blocke before the people of God, who were alſo enlightned, and ſo are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as you knowe fallen with him to the ſame ſinne, and vnder the ſame condemnation. And M. Iarvaſe Nevile haveing witnſſed not onely this but divers other truths for the which he hath bene long impriſoned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to perpetuall impriſoment yea expecting death for the ame, yet notwithſtanding all his former fidelity and conſtancie whereby his bondes were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous through the whole land, falling with M. Smyth vpon this your blind Succeſsion (forſakeing the rock whereon he ſtood) is now returned beyond his vomytt, exclayming againſt your Succeſsion, and ſtrives to build vp the Succeſsion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rome, which he hath formerly, with all zeale and holines pulled downe, &amp; ſo is become a hiſſinge of men, and a reproach vnto all the godly, and is made a ſcorne of the wicked a iuſt reward for all that fall away.</p>
               <p>More over this wicked man Mr. Smyth hath profeſſed and maintened with all manifeſtation of faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that Chriſt tooke his fleſh of Mary, affirming that all the world was not able to aunſwere that place to the Hebr. 2.14. where it is ſaid: foraſmuch, as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren are partakers of fleſh and blood, he alſo himſelf likewiſe tooke part with them, as alſo that place Gen. 3.15. The ſeed of the woman ſhall breake the ſerpents head, but now he is fallen from this, following a device of ſome of you. He cannot find in all the ſcriptures where Chriſt had the firſt matter of his fleſh: but the ſecond matter which is his nouriſhment, that he had of Mary,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17434:18"/> ſaieing further that if he had the ſtrength of many men, he would labor to caſt the contrary out of the Church for being a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> article of faith, &amp; he hath taught that Chriſtes myracles, ſufferinges, and death, yea his hanging vpon the croſſe were all typicall and Carnall, Comparing Chriſt fleſh to his garments, and therefore not to be ſtriven about. So like wiſe is he fallen from the faith of juſtification by Chriſts righteouſnes onely, to inherent righteouſnes in himſelf, ſo wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l he be juſtified partly by his owne righteouſnes, either not ſtanding need of all Chriſts righteouſnes, orels not holding his righteouſnes ſufficient for him. And he is alſo fallen from the faith in the point of Magiſtracie, profeſſing he knew not that he differed from you in anie thinge.</p>
               <p>Further more this wicked man Mr. Smyth hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and taught, and his confederates had learned. That God is a ſpirit, and that he wilbe worſhipped wholly in ſpirit and truth. And he and they knewe that the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle 1. Cor. 14.14.15.16. ſaith. If I pray in a ſtrainge to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue my ſpirit praieth, but myne vnderſtanding is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit. I will pray therefore with the ſpirit, but I will pray with the vnderſtanding alſo. I will ſinge with the ſpirit, but I will ſinge with the vnderſtanding alſo. Els how ſhall they that vnderſtand not, ſay Amen. and verſ. 11. Except I knowe the power of the voice, I ſhalbe vnto him that ſpeaketh a Barbarian. This man not with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when he had himſelf but a little vnderſtanding of your language, and the reſt of his confedracie, when ſome of them had not anie vnderſtanding to be ſpoken of, and divers none at all, neither yet have: have, and do come to worſhipp with you, being barbarians vnto you and ſay Amen (els what do they there) not knowing whether you bleſſe or curſe.</p>
               <p>The ignorant Papiſts ſhall ſtand vp in judgment againſt theſe men, yea the Idolatrous Heathens who have not knowne &amp; heard the thinges that theſe men have knowne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17434:19"/> and hard. Of ſuch men as this and they that are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len with him, ſpeakes Th-appoſtle Iude. VVoe be vnto them: for they have followed the way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayne, and are caſt away by the deceipt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the gaine ſaying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, which you might all right well ſee, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee doubt not but ſome of you do ſee, for you knowe then vnderſtanding in your language, and for what cauſe can you ymagine that they ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unne to gaze at you. Th-appoſtle 1. Cor. 14.19. ſaith. I had rather ſpeake to the Church or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fyve words with myne vnderſtanding that I might alſo inſtruct others, then Ten thouſand words in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge tongue. And doth not The-appoſtle reach heere that it is better to heare fyve words in the Church or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation with vnderſtanding, then Ten-thouſand words in a ſtrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g tongue? But theſe men, with a ſort of ween on that are void of vnderſtanding had rather heare in your Church or congregation fyve words without anie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, then Ten thouſand with vnderſtanding in a congregation or Church gathered together by the preaching of the goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and baptized into his name vpon the confeſsion of their faith and ſinnes.</p>
               <p>This they knewe was our begininge: but your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining they knewe not neither can knowe, and if you had anie other begining it is not according to gods word: but that is all one to them, they have not regarded how you began in the faith, nor how you ſtand in the faith, which (if they had not forſaken all religion) they would have had regard of: but religion was not, nor is not theire marke that they aymed at<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as you may eaſilie deſcerne by theſe their wilfull b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind courſes, where into you have ledd them by your blind Succeſsion.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17434:19"/>
               <p>Now you, and betwixt you and vs, and let all the godly on ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n conſider, whether you have walked vprightly herein or no, and whether you have not ſought your ſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not the glorie of god, nor our building vp in the faith. And thus wee leave the Succeſſion of your baptiſme, putting you in remembrance that vvee have ſhewed you, that by this your opinion you make Iohn baptiſt his example a perticuler example for one man, for what man you cannot tell, but whoſe ever can firſt light of it he hath the pre heminence, and this you ymagine was your firſt beginner, which you ſhall never be able to prove except you can knowe all thinges that are done vnder the ſunne, but all this in you is vanitie of vanities as wee truſt manie of you will eaſilie ſee, and wee wiſh all may. And for this people who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unne after your inventions, of whome wee would not once have made mention, but the better to bring you to the ſight of the greatnes of your ſinne, and to ſett them out for an example that others might be warned thereby, which vvee deſire that they may be, vvhen they ſhall heare of ſuch a people, vvhoſe knovvled, gifts, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vvere great, and vvho vvalked, &amp; preferred to vvalke, ſtrictly by the rules of Chriſt, &amp; vnder his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k, and now are they Behall, walking by no rule of Chriſt, not being vnder his yock, haveing diſclaymed themſelves for haveing anie power to the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e thinges, and have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all to you, all their religion being onely to come and gaze at you, vvho ſpeake to them in a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aing tongue, vvhich is given for a ſigne n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t vnto them that beleeve but vnto them that beleeve not 1. Cor. 14.22. And in that they are thus left in confuſion not knovveing nor careing vvhether to go, vvee have cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to magnifie the name of god in that he hath confounded them in their vvaies that vvould have confounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vvay of truth: and vvee have cruſe to bleſſe god that hath prevented you and kept you from makeing
<pb facs="tcp:17434:20"/> them to be one with you, whereby you had ſtrengthned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their evill, &amp; enlarged your owne ſinne excedingly.</p>
               <p>Let vs now proceed to the Succeſſion of your Church and miniſtry, for wee cannot conceive which way you wilbe able ever to make anie ſhewe or cullor, that this vnbaptized man ſhould have commiſſion to do all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, if your rule of particuler proportion be good, there is no ſuch courſe nor proportion in the ſcriptures. Iohn his example will not ſerve your turne, for Iohn planted no Churches. If you will have planters of Churches, and that all men muſt come to them, then muſt they needs be endued with like gifts as the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanters were, ſpeake all languages as Th-appoſtles did, worke miracles, and not err in doctrine, for the Lords hand is not ſhortned, nor his grace and mercie leſſned to his Church and people. But if he ſend men with the ſame office and aucthoritie, that he ſent his Appoſtles, he will for the honor of his owne name, the advancement of his truth, and good of his people, give them the ſame gifts, and not bring his truth and people in bondage to men full of errors, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and blindnes, as you and all men are: therefore be content to be biulders vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foundation layd, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid not others to build thereon, but let every man take heed how he buildeth vpon it. 1. Cor. 3.10. This may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce for this point and ſo wee come to that, to the which the beſt approved amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, have had no word of ann<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere hetherto, &amp; wee knowe you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay nothinge for it, holding your rule of Succeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to your courſe and proportion except you wilbe ſo very vnadviſed, as to hold proportion in one thinge, &amp; no proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in another, and this that wee intend to ſpeake of, is your miniſtry.</p>
               <p>How come you to raiſe a miniſtry? where is your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler example, your rule is that Elders muſt make El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and none but Elders muſt adminiſter in the holie thinges. You raiſe baptiſme after Iohns examples: but how will you do to ordeyne Elders? ſeeing you have
<pb facs="tcp:17434:20"/> no ſuch exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, &amp; when you have done, what device will you have to keepe this auctoritie to your ſelves? This is your ground for your Succeſsion, as all had baptiſme from Iohn the firſt baptizer, ſo all muſt have baptiſme from your firſt baptizer, As all Churches proceeded from the firſt Church at Ieruſalem, ſo all Churches muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from Ieruſalem your firſt Church. As Elders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by ordination from the firſt Elders, ſo all Elders muſt proceed by ordination from your firſt Elders; heere is your proportion. But how came your Elders by their ordination? did they ordeyne themſelves? where is your example and proportion for that? Did the Church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then your proportion is gone, for the firſt El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were not ſo ordeyned. Thus are you overtaken in your ground not ſeeing whether it ledd you. Forſake it, it ſhalbe no diſgrace for you to forſake error, you ſhall therein ſhewe the true grace of God to be in you, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying your ſelves and your owne waies, and advancing the way of the Lord. Hold you to the perfect rule, that all gaynſaiers are not able to withſtand, which was given by the law giver, and that is. VVhere two, or three are gathered together into my name, there am I in the midſt of them and whatſoever they bind on earth, ſhalbe bound in heaven: and what ſoever they looſe on earth, ſhalbe looſed in heaven. Mat. 18.20.18. And 1. Cor. 3.16.21.22. Knowe you not that yee are the Temple of god. Lett no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioyce in men, for all thinges are yours and 2. Cor. 6.15.16.17.18. what Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord hath Chriſt with Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all; or what part hath the beleever with the infidell: and what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols: wherefore come out from amongſt them and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate yourſelves ſaith the Lord, &amp; touch none vncleane thinge, &amp; I will receive you, &amp; I wilbe a father vnto you, and you ſhalbe my ſonnes, and daughters ſaith the Lord almightie. Theſe three places of ſcripture proves thus much. Firſt, that whereſoever two, or three are gathered
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17434:21"/> together in Chriſts name, Chriſt is in the midſt of them, and they have power to bind and looſe, which is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in &amp; caſt out, to appoint Officers and to diſcharge, and to adminiſter in all the holy thinges, for haveing Chriſt they have wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h him all thinges alſo Rom. 8.32. Chriſts power cannot be devided from him, therefore where he is, his power muſt needs be, &amp; he is a kinge, &amp; where he is, he gives power to his ſervants to ſerve him in all his ordinances.</p>
               <p>The ſecond place alleged confirmes this, where it is ſaid. Let no man reioyce in men, for all thinges are yours, and in the 5. verſ. of this. 1. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. ſaith The Appoſtle, who is Paul? and who is Appollos? but the miniſters by whome ye beleeved, ſheweing that the Cornithians were not the Temple of God, neither had intereſt vnto all thinges, becauſe of their perſons, but becauſe they beleeved their doctrine. And whereſoever a compaine of men now, ſhall beleeve their doctrine, even they are the Temple of god, and all thinges are theirs, aſwell as all thinges were the Corinthians.</p>
               <p>The third place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore alleged, proves, who they are that Chriſt hath promiſſed to be in the midſt of, &amp; that is, thoſe that ſeperate themſelves from Behall (which are men without a yock) from vnbeleevers, from Idolls, and which touch no vncleane thinge, theſe are they that God will receive, and amonge whome he will dwell &amp; walke and he wilbe their God and father, &amp; they ſhalbe his people &amp; children, &amp; they ſhall not need to reſpect the perſons of men as hath bene ſhewed, for by the free gift of Gods grace, &amp; through their faith in Chriſt, all thinges are thens. Will anie men not withſtanding all this ſay, that anie people or congregation ſeperated from all vncleannes, may not enioy Chriſt and all the holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances without they be admitted there vnto by other
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17434:21"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en? Did Th-appoſtle Paule diſclayme both for himſelf, and Cephas, &amp; Appollos from all previlige vnto their perſons, &amp; teach the corinthians that their perſons gave not them intereſt vnto the holie things but their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine through their owne faith; and dare anie chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge previlege vnto their perſons, &amp; ſo take away the the aucthoritie of Th-appoſtles doctrine &amp; miniſterie, that is ſtill in as good force &amp; aucthoritie as ever, in the ſcriptures. And by whoſe miniſterie &amp; doctrine what people ſoever beleeves at this day, all thinges are the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, by faith in the ſcriptures not by Succeſsion from men.</p>
               <p>Heere wee deſire that all men that have anie vprightnes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, would enter into a due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the depth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> error of Succeſsion, from, or by the perſons of men. And through gods aſsiſtance wee will endeavour to ſpeake what wee are able for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie of this error, which is ſo great &amp; dangerous, of the ſharpe bitter fruites whereof, wee have deepely tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, &amp; our vvounds are yet freſh &amp; greene: but not vvithſtanding by the grace of God, vvee vvill not be provoked to ſpeake beyond the bounds of ſobriet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein: and to proceed herein by the moſt eaſie, plaine, and evident vvay to our beſt vnderſtandings.</p>
               <p>VVee intreat you, and all men vvith all holy adviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to conſider, vvhat vvas the ſeperation vvall, betvvixt the Ievve &amp; the gentill, &amp; Th-appoſtle Rom. 3.1.2. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares plainely what is vvas in theſe vvords. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of the Ievve &amp; the profitt of circumciſion is much everie manner of vvay, for cheiflie becauſe vnto them were of creditt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the oracles of god, this was the diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvall, vvhich the Lord had ſet vp betvvixt the Iewe &amp; the gentill in that he gave his ſtatutes &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces to Iſraell to keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, not debarring the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tills at all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioying the benefitt of his ſtatutes &amp; ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces as the lord ſheweth Exo. 12.49. One lavv ſhalbe to him that is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17434:22"/> borne in the land, and to the ſtrainger that dwelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you. This then was the preferment and the devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wall, that the Iewes kept the oracles, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tills muſt have them at their hands: for if the gentills had themſelves poſſeſſed the land of Canaan. And the holie Citie, and the Temple; and all the holie thinges they had bene all polluted in their hands; but when the Iewes had the poſſeſſion of all the holy thinges, and communicated them vnto the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tills they were holy to them. Thus could the gentills have no benifitt of the holy thinges, except they came to the Iewes and receyved them from them, and ſo enioyed them vnder them. This then is ſo plaine as anie thinge can be, that the partition wall betwixt the Iewe and the gentill, was in reſpect of the previlige that belonged to the perſon of the Iewe, in that, to the perſon of the Iewes, the oracles were committed to be kept, for as wee have ſhewed there was the ſame law of ordinances for the gentill as for the Iewe, but the gentill muſt receive them from the Iewes, and they muſt come vp to Ieruſalem to worſhip with the jewes Act 8.27. and joh. 4.20. This ſtopp of the partition wall hath Chriſt broken downe. That he might reconcile both vnto God in one body, by his croſſe and ſlay hatred thereby, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keing peace Eph. 2.16.15. Thus hath the Lord of himſelf made peace both with jewe &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>till, now not preferring anie one people above another in giveing his oracles to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to keepe, but hath made his convenant with all, both jewe, &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>till, they that are a farr of, &amp; they that are neare Act. 2.39. Eph. 2.17. To everie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth good ſhalbe glorie and honor and peace, to the jew firſt, and alſo to the grecian. For there is no reſpect of perſons with god Rom. 2.10.11. There are now by gods appointment no more ſtraingers and forreyners, but through Chriſt, all both jew and gentile, have an entrance vnto the father by one ſpirit Epheſ. 2.19.18. not ſtanding in need of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by men. And what people ſoever, either jew, or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17434:22"/> gentile, are biult vpon the foundation of Th-appoſtles and Prophetts Ieſus Chriſt himſelf being the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, in whome all the building cuppled together, groweth vnto an holie Temple in the Lord, they are built together to be the habitation of god by the ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epheſ. 2.20.21.22. And therefore no people are bound to ſeeke to men to be built a habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god: But the doctrine of Th-appoſtles by the worke of the ſpirit is ſufficient. All this proves the partition wall is broken downe, which is, that the oracles are not now commited to anie people of creditt to keepe that all ſhould be forced to come to them as the gentills were of neceſsitie conſtrayned to come to the jewes, Chriſt hath ſlayne that hatred ſaith Th-appoſtle, and hath reconciled the gentills to god, and ſo god is equally favourable to them both, that is to all men (for all were either jewes or gentils) God doth not favour anie one in reſpect of committing his orracles to be kept, they are now left free to all that come, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that prophecie of ſcripture Pſai. 55.1. Hoe every one that thirſteth come ye to the waters, and ye that have no ſilver come buy and eate. Come I ſay buy wine and mylke without ſilver and without monie.</p>
               <p>This then being confeſſed of al (that have anie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in the religion of God) that the ſeperation wall is broken downe, and being rightly vnderſtood alſo that the ſeperation wall was a perſonall previlige vnto the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar nation of the jewes by genealogie, which was to keepe the oracles of God by Succeſſion amongſt them ſelves, from generation to generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the gentiles that were without could not be admitted to the holy thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges but by them, this being the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>viſion vvall, and this being broken dovvne, and the gentiles let in, &amp; the doore ſett open for all, &amp; freedome &amp; libertie proclaymed. That by the blood of jeſus chriſt vvee may be bold to enter into the holy place, by the nevv and liveing vvay,
<pb facs="tcp:17434:23"/> which he hath prepared for vs through the vaile, that is his fleſh Heb. 10.1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20. Hereby all Succeſſion is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, all previlige and pr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ment to perticuler perſons in keeping the holy oracles is taken away, and they are free for all men, (that beleeve to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for wee are all the ſonnes of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus, There is neither Iewe, nor Grecian: there is neither bond, nor free <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e is neither male nor feemale: or we are all one in Chriſt Ieſus Gal. 3.26.8. Now they then that will ſet vp Succeſsion, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have all the orac<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of God committed to them, and that all <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ordinances of Chriſt from them they herein build vp the per<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> wall againe they challenge to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Iewe they ſtopp the entrance into the holie place by the new and liveing way, which Chriſt hath made by his blood: they deny that any people built vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appoſtles &amp; Prophetts by the ſpirit, can be the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on of God they will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the ſonnes of god by faith: all theſe thinges are nothinge available without me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; be ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted by them: &amp; men cannot have Chriſt except they have the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor be joyned to chriſt, except they be ioyned to them: nor putt on christ except they putt on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lett all the godly but equally iudg betwixt you and vs, whether this be not to ſett vp the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wall againe, W<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h is to give a ſpeciall previlege <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the people more then another and that none may enioy the holy thinges but from their perſons, which wee de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e may yet better be obſerved, &amp; well vnderstood, that you, or what people ſoever manteyne Succeſsion o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will have a previlege or preferment, in the poſſeſſion of the holie things it doth apperteyne &amp; is tyed to your perſons &amp; the power and auctoritie you challenge it is in your perſons, for it is not in your gifts a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doctrine for ſet<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by your perſones &amp; tye vs not to them, and then wee will preferr the gifts &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Th-appoſtles before yours, and wee wilbe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17434:23"/> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the aucthoritie and preferment you chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is not in your office, for ſett by your perſons and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall preſence, and ſend precepts &amp; rules, by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of your Office and wee, and all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare god will caſt away your aucthoritie and office and the aucthoritie and office of all others heerein, with the precepts and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les made by the power thereof, and wee will onely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt our ſelves to the office and aucthoritie of Th-appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and to the precepts and rules, which they have ſett downe by the power of their office, wch power a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d office they received fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, not from men, nor by man gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Thus may you and all men ſee, that what people chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, or congregation ſoever do challenge vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves anie previlige or preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in keeping the holy thinges, &amp; that they onely are to diſpoſe of the to others, ſuch previlige, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t muſt needs be proper to their perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s onely and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſuch previlige to their perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as wee have be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhewed Paul, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>phas, and Appollos diſclaymes, although they were the miniſters by whome the corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians beleeved. And will you, or anie people or church challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge privilege and preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your perſons over al men, although by your miniſtrie they beleeve not: and all your warrant for this is becauſe you ſay, you are the firſt.</p>
               <p>If you wil yet ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for privilege by your beeing fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> as you Ymagine) heare what our ſaviour chriſt ſaith vnto you for your inſtruction Mat. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rend I do thee no wronge, take that which is thyne owne, and go thy way. I will give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> much as vnto thee: theſe men thought becauſe they came firſt into the veinya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d they ſhould have had more wage them they that came laſt, although there wages were agreed vpon, ſo you thinke you are worthie of more aucthoritie, them the laſt becauſe you ſuppoſe you were the firſt: but our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour chriſt teacheth you in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> place that the honor &amp; reward in all one to the laſt, as to the firſt. And take heed, leaſt by this your ſinne, if you had no other) the lord paſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17434:24"/> this ſentence againſt you, and ſay vnto you. The firſt ſhalbe laſt.</p>
               <p>To dravve to an end in this point, that the goſpell is come vnto all the vvorld alike coll. 1.6. to god is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter of perſons: And therefore all the world ought to receive it, beleeve it, &amp; obey it a like: &amp; ſo doeing, all have free libertie to enioy and adminiſter in all the holy ordinances a like: for of vvhomeſoever the Lord requires obedience of all his ordinances, they obeying, he giveth to them the privilege &amp; benifitt of all his ordinances. Then vvhat ſoever people receives, beleeves, &amp; obeyes the goſpell, as truely as another people do, they have as much privilege &amp; libertie to einoy the goſpel &amp; all the ordinances thereof as anie other people: For god is no accepter of perſons, but in every Nation, he that feareth him &amp; vvorketh righteouſnes is accepted vvith him Act. 10.34.35. And if anie ſhall novv feare god, &amp; faſt &amp; pray as Cornelius did, their praiers &amp; almes ſhall come vp in remembrance before god &amp; the ſpirit of god ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them to heare vvhat Peter ſaith, &amp; to be directed by Peter, &amp; the reſt of Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appoſtles, &amp; not bid them ſend for you, or go to you, or anie people to make them perfect, for the word of God is all ſufficient to teath them &amp; inſtruct them &amp; make them perfect to everie good vvorke, as is ſhevved. 2. tim. 3.16.17. The vvhole ſcriptures as given by inſpiration of god, &amp; is profitable to teath to convine, to correct, &amp; to inſtruct in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that the man of god may be abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes. Heere may you &amp; all learne &amp; vnderſtand, that the vvord of god is all ſufficient of it ſelf, to make the people of god abſolute &amp; perfect vnto every good worke, to pray, to preach, to Baptize, to breake bread, to adminiſter in all the holy thinges &amp; to vvalke in all the vvaies of god, vvithout the helpe of of anie man or men. And if anie ſhould be ſo vnvviſe, as thinke that the meaning of the holy ghoſt heere is onely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17434:24"/> to make a man perfect vnto everie good worke in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, it were great weaknes, ſeeing that the holy ghoſt teſtifieth, That the mainfeſtation of the ſpirit is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to every man to profit withall. 1. Cor, 12.7. &amp; 1. Pet. 4.10. Lett everie man as he hath received the gift Miniſter the ſame to another, as good diſpoſers of the manifold graces of god. To make this plaine that he that runnes may read it &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it that Chriſt and al things are geven to every faithfull people, although they be but two or three according to Chriſtes owne wordes Mat. 18.20. Chriſt is there king Luk. 1.33. he is there Mediator Heb. 9.15. by whoſe blood they may be bould to enter into the holy place. He is their high Prieſt, who with one offering hath conſecrated for ever the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſanctified Heb. 10.21.14. And made them kings, And Preiſts vnto God Reuel. 1.6. They are come vnto Mount Syon. And to the citie of the liveing God the celeſtiall Ieruſalem Heb. 12.22. whoſe gates are not ſhutt by day, and there is no night there Reuel. 21.25. wee conclude therefore with thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wordes of comfort ſpoken by the holy ghoſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everie faithfull man, and men though but two or three. Reuel. 22.17. Both the ſpirit &amp; the Bride ſay co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. And let him that heareth, ſay, come, and let him that is a thirſt, come, and let who ſoever will, take of the water of life freely.</p>
               <p>VVe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with your ſelves now, and let all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſider, whether this be not al ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Heere is the King: &amp; the Mediator: and the high Prieſt: and the citie Ieruſalem with hir gates open: and the ſpirit of God bidding all come freely: and all the faithfull made kings, &amp; Preiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vnto God, what ſhould let the faithfull for entring in, &amp; offering Sacrifices, &amp; adminiſtring in all the holy thinges before the lord, ſeeing they onely are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there vnto of God. 1. Pet. 2.5. &amp; 4.10.</p>
               <p>If the jewes cominge out of captivitie, had had Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17434:25"/> their kinge, Moſes their mediator, Aaron their high Prieſt, Ieruſalem their citie with hir gates open &amp; their god bidding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come, who ſhould have for bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for bringing their ſacrifices and adminiſtring before the lord freely. If Pharoh ſhould hinder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the plagues of Egipt ſhould fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And though Tobiah ſhould deſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ballett co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire againſt them, yet they praying to their god their enimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſhame ſhould be turned vpon their owne heads, and the lord ſhould bring their counſells to nought Nehe. 4. And God hath promiſſed to do no leſſe for his people now againſt his and their enimie the miſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, the man of ſinne for he will conſume him with the ſpirit of his mouth, &amp; aboliſh him with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his coming 2. Theſ. 2.8. And he will ſmyte the earth with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of his mouth and with the breath of his lipps ſhall he ſlay the wicked Eſa. 11.4.</p>
               <p>Now therefore take you heed, and let al people ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ficed, how they go about to hinder the people of god that have freedome and libertie to adminiſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, being a holy Preiſthood to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt 1. Pet. 2.5. take heed wee ſay how you go about to hinder them, by ſetting vp your owne inventions and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and bring ſwiſt iudgment vpon your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves. And ſo wee leave this point praying you not lightly to paſſe by it though wee have handled it weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly But let all that diſire vnfainedly in the truth of their ſoules to ſee the profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt florriſh in puritie and ſincerity, and in the light of all truth, ſett their owne harts and teach others to ſeeke Chriſt in his word: And to followe him in all worſhipp and ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice according to the examples, rules &amp; precepts in the Striptures, which are written for vs to that end. For, what ſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inges are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aforetime are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing Rom. 15.1.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17434:25"/>
               <p>Lett all men therefore that in vprightnes diſires to walke in the waies of god according to true direction, ſeeke to be taught of god by the Scriptures, and not to be ledd by the examples and precepts of men: For if a people though but two, or three, by reading and hearing the Scriptures, by the worke of the ſpirit, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to the faith of the goſpel, muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to joyne to anie, or ſome people that formerly profeſſe Chriſt, then muſt they be forced, to profeſſe as they profeſſe, and walke in their ſtepps with them: and ſo to be brought in ſubiection to all their errors, and to be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by joyning with them in all their corruptions and ſo they cannot nor muſt not be ledd on for ward towards perfection as they ought to be Heb. 6.1. But they muſt be ledd forward or go backward, or out of the way, or ſtand ſtill, as that people to whome they joyne will lead them. This deſtroyes all pure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the goſpell, and keepes men backe from wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the cleare light thereof: ffor if two or three ſhall in the honeſtie of their harts diſire to walke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e with the lord, and keepe themſelves vnſpotted of error, this wofull rule of Succeſſion debarrs them that they may not ſo do, and conſtraines them to joyne to ſome people, denying them libertie to walke after the rules and examples in the Scriptures and ſo to followe Chriſt, and binds them to followe Chriſt with them, as they followe Chriſt. Hence it cometh that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſaith, loe heere is Chriſt, and ſeekes to force all to followe Chriſt with him. And the Biſhopps they ſay loe heere is Chriſt and they ſeeke to compell all to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe Chriſt with them. The Preſbitarie they ſay, loe heree is Chriſt, and they will conſtraine all to followe Chriſt with them, wee paſſe by the moſt vngodly &amp; vnwiſe Familiſts and ſcattered flock, that ſay he is in the deſert, that is no where to be found in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goſpell according to the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces thereof
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17434:26"/> vntill their extraordinarie men (they dreame of) come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which ſhall not be, vntil there come a new Chriſt, &amp; a new goſpell. And you to whome wee eſpecially write you ſay loe heere is Chriſt, &amp; you would have all to followe Chriſt with you. Now in theſe trobleſome dayes which our ſauiour Chriſt hath foretold of, and are now come to paſſe wherein if it were poſſible the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry elect ſhould be deceaved, let all the godly ſtay them ſelves vpon that bleſſed counſel of our Saviour Chriſt who ſaith vnto al that will followe him, take yee heed, behold I have ſhewed you althinges before Mark. 13.23. which is by his word, and therefore thither onely muſt wee go, and followe no men. And wee pray al you (that would have men followe Chriſt with you) to remember how our Saviour Chriſt reproved his Diſciples for their evill diſpoſition therin, who when they ſawe one caſting out deviles in Chriſtes name for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badd him becauſe he followed not Chriſt with them. Ieſus vtterly diſaproving them, ſaid, forbidd yee him not, he that is not againſt vs is with vs. Luk. 9.49.50 If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſaviour Chriſt would not ſuffer theſe his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves this privilege, nor would not reſtraine that his Diſciple, for profeſſinge his name althoug he followed not with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why ſhould anie chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, or why ſhould the people of god think them ſelves bound to give vnto anie this prerogative.</p>
               <p>Let all the people of God therefore every where knowe, that they have libertie to followe Chriſtly them ſelves, which if Gods people would practice with feare &amp; reverence, relying onely vpon the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of gods word &amp; ſpirit, it would make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wary &amp; carefull of their waies, leaſt they ſhould run into error, &amp; ſo be iuſtly reproved of all, whift all mens eies are vpon them; whereas contrariwiſe, if of neceſſitie they be bound to go &amp; joyne to another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, they walke ſecurely, becauſe that people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17434:26"/> walking is their warrant and what ſoever they find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them muſt be received as approved &amp; good. And this makes divers, who often receives manie good motions of the ſpirit to quench thoſe provocations of the ſpirit, becauſe they thinke they muſt needes ioyne to ſome people, and can ſee none that walke ſo vpright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; nolilie, with whome they may have comfort to joyne: &amp; this is a cheife cauſe of all this evill, in that manie are blinded with this error that you, &amp; all the fore named people do ſtand ſo ſtiffly vpon, that they muſt joyne to the Church. And ſo is this libertie hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from their eies (you all that teach that doctrine being inſtrumentes there of) that they may joyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves to gether in the covenant of the new Teſtament, &amp; ſo be the church &amp; Temple of God them ſelves as well as you or anie people: and through the gracions bleſſing of god, which he hath promiſſed ſhalbe vpon them, they ſo doeing &amp; walking in his waies, they may, &amp; ſhall growe to be a moſt holy people, and a houſe for the moſt high god to dwel in, the word &amp; ſpirit of god being fullie ſufficient to build them vp, &amp; they edifieing one another in their moſt holy faith, according to the rules of the holy ghoſt in the new Teſtament: And all this without the authoritie or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of anie people profeſſing before them, but all this you hide from their eies.</p>
               <p>O that the children of god were as wiſe in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in al thinges, &amp; in this, as the Sonnes of men, then would they looſe no part of that libertie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt hath made them free, then would every people called of god, runne of them ſelves, the rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before them, and followe hard toward the marke, for the price of the high calling of god in Chriſt Ieſus Phil. 3.14. Vnto the which till the called of god by the word of his ſpirit, raiſe vp their hartes to do, ſtriveing withall zeale &amp; holines to runne one before another
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17434:27"/> in the profesſion of the truth, till theſe gracions affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and holie endeavours poſſeſſe the harts and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men, there can be no hope to ſee the glorious light of Gods truth in the profesſion thereof to flor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh &amp; growe: ffor whilſt ſome Church or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſettled in the dreggs of error, and overtaken with a ſecure, cold, frozen profesſion of the goſpel, and ſome other church or congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carried away with a head-ſtronge blind zeale into manie errors, will have all men come and followe Chriſt, or rather go out of the way, or be frozen vp with them, and while men thinke they are to give them this preferment, what hope is there of the groth of pure Religion. VVe therefore earneſtly beſeech all people, by the mercies of god (in whome there is anie faithfull love of gods truth) not to reſpect anie men, neither to followe Chriſt, as you have them for an example: but followe Chriſt as you are taught is his word, and as you have the holy mens examples, whoſe holines is approved in the Scriptures. And thus in all love, wee exhort you to be thus mynded by the name of Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Although this that hath bene manifeſted from the Scriptures may give full ſatisfaction to every faithfull holie profeſſor of the goſpell (that Chriſt by his preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce giveth all power to every congregation, aſwell as to anie one people or congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gathered together in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his name, though they be but two, or three, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be firſt gathered or laſt gathered: whether there be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lder, or no Elders amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is with god all one) wet becauſe amongſt all (almoſt) that profeſſe Chriſt, there is ſo much a doe about ordination, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, as though olders hands were onely ſanctified to that vſe, wee pray the godly reader to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive full ſatisfaction from Act. 13.1.2.3. where it doth evidently appeare that the church or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia (where there were no Appoſtles nor elders) by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17434:27"/> the direction of the holy ghoſt, with faſting, &amp; praying, &amp; laying on of hands ſeperated Paull &amp; Barnabas to the worke of their miniſterie, wherevnto the holy ghoſt had called them. And Paul went not to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that were Appoſtles before him, not ſo much as to conſult with them Gal. 1.17. but after they were ſeperated by the church, being ſent furth by the holy ghoſt they came downe to Seleucia. Act. 13.4. And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this time did firſt begin to adminiſter in the Office of their Appoſtle ſhip: in all this let it obſerved, that it is here ſet downe expreſly in the ſcriptures; that they were called vnto their office of god &amp; ſet furth of god, &amp; that the church did onely ordeyne, or ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that worke: and therefore this doth nothinge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict Gala. 1.1. where it is ſaid Paul an Appoſtle, not of men, neither by man: for he was called &amp; ſent of god. Thus is it proved that the church or congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath power (with faſting &amp; praier) to lay on hands, and ſo to ſeparate &amp; ordeyne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> choſen, to adminiſter. And this is the ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet downe in the ſcriptures, which moſt men make ſo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat an Idoll of. And wee hope wee ſhall not need to prove perticulerly that the church or congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath power to Elect or chuſe their officers ſeeing that is ſo plainely ſet downe Act. 14.23. &amp; 6.3.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Magiſtracie.</head>
               <p>THE fowrth matter that by the aſſiſtance of God wee purpoſe to ſpeake to you of, is, to prove vnto you, and all that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie mynded. That king, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Magiſtrats, ruleing &amp; governing by the power of god, with the ſword of Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, may be members of the church of Chriſt reteyning their Magiſtracie. For proofe hereof Thappoſtle Paul to the Rom. 13.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. firſt ſheweth (ſpeaking of the higher powers) That all powers are ordeyned of god. And who ſoever reſiſteth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17434:28"/> the power reſiſtes the Ordinance of God. This then hereby is made moſt plaine, that the power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Magiſtrates is the holy ordinance of God. They are further called. The miniſters of god, and their adminiſtration is ſet downe. To take vengance of them that do evill, and to praiſe them that do well, And the inſtrument wherewith they are to puniſh evill doers, is the ſword. And in all this they are the miniſters of god for good &amp; for the good of gods children eſpecially. And therefore are they comaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to pray for them 1. Tim. 2.12. Thus is their power (being of god) holie &amp; good: and their office &amp; admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration holie, &amp; good being (as is heere ſhewd by Th-appoſtle) appointed of god for good, who doth, nor can appoint nothinge but that which is holie &amp; good, and pleaſing to himſelf, for he is holines &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes it ſelf, and he may not, nor cannot appoint anie thinge contrary to himſelf.</p>
               <p>God then haveing ordeyned &amp; appointed this holy ordinance with the end, and vſe of it, and manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtration, the magiſtrates applieing them ſelves for the ſame thinge, they obey the holy comandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and will of god, &amp; are pleaſing and acceptable to the lord in that their obedience: for by theſe wordes. Applying themſelves there vnto. The holy ghoſt intends and ſhewes, that ther is required a diligent willing, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obedience in their adminiſtration, and not a forced conſtrained obedience, as the devills obey god, whoſe obedience is not acceptable and wel pleaſing vnto him: further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is wel pleaſed in ſheweing the power of his owne might, in that comaunding them they muſt obey him: for the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> do not willingly obey god in anie thing. They do not willingly knowe god as appeareth when they cried Mat. 8.29. Ieſus the ſonne of god, what have wee to do with thee: and although they bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e there is one god, yet they do it not willingly,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17434:28"/> becauſe they tremble Iam. 2.19. there faith increaſeth their feare. All this wee ſpeake to make it plaine to the ſimpleſt: ffirſt, that there is an obedience which god comandes by the word and worke of his power onely, where in they that obey pleaſe not god: as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the vncleane ſpirits to come furth, and they obeyed him: And thus did Pharoh obey, when he let the people of Iſraell go to ſerve the lord, as Moſes and Aaron had ſaid Exo. 12.31. this was no willing obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and therefore not acceptable vnto god. Secondly there is an obedience, which god comandes by the word and worke of his grace, wherein, and whereby they that obey, pleaſe god, and are acceptable vnto him. This is the obedience that is better then Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
               <p>And this is the obedience that god requires of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Princes, and Magiſtrates, even a diligent, willing, faithfull obedience, as is ſhewed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe words: They are the miniſters of god applieing them ſelves for the ſame thinge. And let vs with all grace and holines vnto god, and revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto this his holy ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, conſider what it is that they are to applie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves vnto. It is to puniſh evil doers with the ſword, and to reward or praiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do well: theſe wordes might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince you all of your error in this point, and they ſhall condemne you all, if you repent not, of your reaching and ſtiftly ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inteyning, that theſe Miniſters of god, retayning this their Office from god, may not be members of the Church of Chriſt. Hearken to their Office or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery yet againe. It is to puniſh evill doers, and to reward or praiſe them that do well, in which holy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration they are like vnto god, and in applieing them ſelves faithfullie therein they do the worke that is proper to god: for to execute juſtice vpon the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ſhewe mercie vnto them that do well, is the divine propertie and worke of god, and ſo farr as the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17434:29"/> lord hath comitted auctoritie to Magiſtrats to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter therein, they do the proper worke of god: and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore doth the holy ghoſt by the Prophett David, ſpeaking of Magiſtrats ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſal. 32.6. I have ſaid yee are gods, ſpeaking in reſpect of the great honor that is due vnto them, by their holie Office, where vnto he hath appointed them.</p>
               <p>The ſome &amp; ſcope of that which is heare ſett downe in this point, is to ſhewe vnto you, that the Appoſtle doth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e teach, that the Office &amp; miniſtery of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats is an holy Office appointed of god, and that the lord requires of Magiſtrats a diligent willing, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, obedience, which is pleaſing vnto the lord: the which obedience they preforming vprightly, though weakely, and fayling in manie thinges, as Th-appoſtle confeſſeth, he &amp; all the children of god did Iam. 3.2 yet beleeving the goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and repenting of their ſinnes, how can it be denyed them to be admitted members of the bodie of Chriſt? Is this a good excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe they are Magiſtrats? why then you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt them becauſe they are the holy miniſters of god, and do his will in faithfull obedience. VVhat a doctrine of devills is this, that anie ſhould be denyed to be members of the body of Chriſt, for executing an holie Office appointed of god. For further proofe, that it is an holy ordinance or office pleaſing vnto god, it is ſhewed in that wee are comanded to obey of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; &amp; that is onely in that which is holy &amp; good; for god forbidd, that his children, ſhould be tyed of conſcience to obey in anie thinge, that is vnholy &amp; not good. Th-appoſtle ſhewes heere, that the holy ghoſt intends no ſuch thinge, when he ſaith vers. 3. Magiſtrats are not to be feared for good works, and 1. Pet 2.17. Feare god: honor the kinge, &amp; therefore if Magiſtrats ſhall comaund anie thinge againſt god or Godlines, the people of god are not bound to obey, &amp; for this cauſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17434:29"/> Th-appoſtles when they were comaunded of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers &amp; Elders of Iſraell, that in no wiſe they ſhould ſpeake or teach in the name of Ieſus, anſwered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right in the ſight of God, to obey you, rather then god, judg yee. All this doth ſtill give further proo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, that Magiſtracie is a holy miniſtery or Office appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inted of god onely for good, and therefore none bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that Office or miniſtery, is, for that cauſe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the body of Chriſt which is his church, except men for executing an office co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of Chriſt, ſhould be debarred from Chriſt, which is more then madnes, for anie that profeſſe Chriſt to affirme.</p>
               <p>Furthermore: hath god by reaſon of that high po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; auctoritie which he hath given to Magiſtrats co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded ſuch feare ſuch obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; ſo great honor to be given vnto them of all men, and ſhall they whome god hath ſo greatly honored, with ſuch auctoritie, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie &amp; power, for, bearing this honor which god hath putt vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall they for this be accounted vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſtes church? This is to bring the greateſt diſhonor, that poſſiblie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be before god &amp; his people, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ordinance &amp; the miniſters thereof vpon which, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome, the lord hath putt moſt honor on: for it is a moſt miſerable, wretched, &amp; diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, office, or calling, that debarrs me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſtes body. And let all knowe, that have anie vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the miſterie of godlines, that if Magiſtrats ought not to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſts church they cannot be childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kingdome of Chriſt; and if they be not children of the kingdome, they cannot be heires of the promiſſe: for thoſe that are worthy to be heires of ſaluation, muſt needs firſt be children of the kingdome, being begotten by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mortall ſeed of the word and borne a new 1. Pet. 1.23. all ſuch are worthy to be members of Chriſts Church.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17434:30"/> Therefore if you vnderſtand your ſelves ſe this to be the end of your opinion. That if, you denying Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and hold them vnworthy to be members of Chriſtes Church, you much more deny them to be worthy of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for if by reaſon of their Office they be vnworthie to be of the comunio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaintes vpon earth, they muſt nedes thereby much more be made vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy to be of the comunion of the Saintes in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thus do you by this your opinion hold and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inteyne, that god hath appointed an ordinance, and they that are his miniſters therein (by his owne appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intement) are by that their Office and miniſtery debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſaluation. Your ſinne herein is no leſſe then blaſphemy againſt god, in that you charge the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have appointed an ordinance, the executing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof debarrs men from ſaluation, wee hope you do it ignorantly, as alſo your leaders. Let not the antiquitie of this your error make it precious vnto you, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vile: and ſinne not by tradition after the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men: but be brought to try your waies by the word of god, and ſet his ſpirit be your teacher and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into all truth, &amp; be not led by men for all men are gone out of the way, and are full of ignorance &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
               <p>And to make it appeare how you are miſledd in this be witched opinion. VVe wil come to ſome of your cheife holdes herein, whereof this is one Mat. 20.25.26. Luk. 22.24.25.26. &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 10.5, 45. There aroſe a ſtrife among Chriſtes diſciples which ſhould be the greateſt; And he ſaid vnto them. The kinges of the gentiles reigne over them, and they that beare rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them are called gracious lords, but ye ſhall not be ſo: but let the greateſt be as the leaſt, and the cheif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt as him that ſerveth. From hence you gather that kings &amp; Magiſtrates that beare rule in the world, may not be of the Church. To come (by the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17434:30"/> of the ſpirit of god) vnto a due vnderſtanding of this ſcripture: wee muſt firſt ſeeke to knowe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein the diſciples of Chriſt did ſeeke to be greater one then another, and if they did ſtrive for worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, then may your ground prove partly true: but if they did not ſtrive for preferment in the world or worldly preferment, then is there no cullor that your collected ground ſhould be true: for our ſaviour Chriſt his ſpeach is to put an end to their ſtrife, &amp; if they did not ſtrive for worldly preferment or who ſhould be greateſt in the world, then our Saviour Chriſt ſpake not at all concerning worldly ſuperiority &amp; rule, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he brought an example from the world which is moſt vſuall in the ſcriptures. This controverſie then wee hope may eaſilie take an end, if you be not vtterly given vp to your owne waies in all thinges: for if the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t will not be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtill, they may by the grace of god ſee heere moſt evidently the ground &amp; cauſe of this ſtrife amongſt the diſciples.</p>
               <p>Zebedeus ſonnes diſired of our Saviour Chriſt, that they might ſitt one at his right hand, and the other at his left in his kingdome not ſpeaking of the world. Our Saviour firſt reproves them ſharply and tells them they knowe not what they aſked. And when he ſaw that this their diſire of ſupirioritie wrought diſdaine amongſt them all, Ieſus called them vnto him, and caught them to knowe. That although the kings &amp; lords of the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles and they that were great amongſt them, had domination &amp; aucthoritie, and bare rule over them, in his kingdome it ſhould not be ſo, He came not to ſett vp and eſtabliſh ſuch a kingdome, wherein men ſhould ſeeke to be greater one then another, and to beare rule one over another: and therefore taught his diſciples another leſſon, telling them that who ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will ſeeke to be great, or be cheifeſt amongſt them in his kingdome, ſhalbe the ſervant of all, that is the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17434:31"/> meaneſt of all, for that pride or arrogancie in ſeeking to be chiefe &amp; beare rule in, the kingdome of Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſuch the leaſt, becauſe god reiecteth &amp; will caſt downe the prowd, but he will exalt the humble. Now as our Saviour Chriſt taught his diſciples heere, by an example from Kings &amp; Rulers and great men, that it ſhould not be ſo amongſt them in his kingdome: So alſo vpon the ſame occation of ſtrife, &amp; queſtion who ſhould be the greateſt Mat. 18.1.4. &amp; Mark. 9.34.36. &amp; Luk. 9.46.48. Our Saviour Chriſt takes a little child &amp; ſetteth it in the mideſt of them, and teacheth them by the example of a child to be humble and lowſy, and ſaith, except they be converted and become as little childre they ſhall not e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter into the kingdome of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And who ſoever ſhall humble himſelf as a little child, the ſame is the greateſt in the kingdome of heaven.</p>
               <p>From the firſt of theſe examples of Kings and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers &amp; great men, becauſe our Saviour Chriſt ſaith. It ſhall not be ſo amongſt you, you ſhall not in my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be like them, that is, Reigne, and rule, and be great one over another.</p>
               <p>From this firſt example you conclude, that Kings, Rulers &amp; great men, may not be of the kingdome of Chriſt. That you may the better ſee the error of this your collection and concluſion, wee will collect and conclude the like from the other example which our Saviour Chriſt brought of a little child.</p>
               <p>He ſaith the Diſciples of his kingdome muſt be like little children, humble, not ſeeking to be greater one then another: therefore little children may be of the kingdome of Chriſt, becauſe our Saviour Chriſt ſaith they muſt be like them, wee knowe you can eaſilie diſcerne the errror of this collection and concluſion, and why can you not de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne the error of the other
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17434:31"/> wee pray you as you love god, and his truth, be not ſo partiall in your ſelves, wee wil yet endeavor to ſhewe you the equall like of theſe concluſions, that you may of conſcience (denying the one) deny the other alſo.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour Chriſt ſaith. The Kings and Rulers; and great men of the Gentiles reigne and rule over them, but it ſhal no be ſo amongſt you the Diſciples of my kingdome: therefore (ſay you) Kings and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and great men may not be of the kingdome of Chriſt. In like manner may it be ſaid (our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaking vpon the ſame occation, little children are humble, and ſeeke not one to be greater then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it ſhalbe ſo amonge you the Diſciples of my king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome: therefore may anie aſwell ſay) little children may be of the kingdome of Chriſt. Seeing you are confident (and that according to truth) that this laſt is not a true collection and concluſion: ſo alſo of conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, acknowled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the firſt, which you make is not true: for as in the laſt both you and wee do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that Chriſt (ſpeaking of his kingdome which is ſpirituall) did teach his Diſciples by the example of a little child, that by reaſon of it yong yeres, was in qualitie and condition humble: ſo he would have them humble in ſpirit; and our Saviour Chriſt doth not teach heere, that little children are ſpiritually humble, and therefore may be of this his kingdome: for infants are but borne of the fleſh; but they muſt be borne againe of the ſpirit, that enter into this kingdome of Chriſt Io. 3. therefore doth our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt heere ſpeake but of qualitie and condition of children; which is to be humble, not tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching hereby that they may be of this his kingdome: Even ſo our Saviour Chriſt the in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17434:32"/> other example (ſpeaking of the power rule, and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of kings, Rulers, and great men) teacheth them, that in his ſpirituall kingdome amongſt his Diſciples, he will not have them as kinges Rulers, and great men to reigne one over another; or to be greater one then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in his kingdome. Not teaching hereby, that kings Rulers, and great men may not be of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt but that his Diſciples may not (as kinge Rulers, and great men) reigne one over another in his kingdome.</p>
               <p>In all this our Saviour Chriſt ſpeakes of his kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me which is ſpirituall: and ſpeakes againſt ſpirituall power and auctoritie, and will not therein that his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſhould ſeeke to be greater one then another not excepting againſt, nor Diſaproveing the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of earthly kinges and Princes, which is his owne holy ordinance, but that they may be of Chriſt, retayning their power and auctoritie, and adminiſtring in their office, and ought to have all due honor and obedience: But if they, or anie ſhall ſeeke to have ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual power, rule and auctority in this kingdome, and therein make them ſelves greater then the reſt of the Diſciples of Chriſt, that is it which our Saviour heere doth altogether ſpeake againſt and disaprove, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re vpon, and in this reſpect teacheth his Diſciples to be humble as little children and not ſeeke in ſpiritual po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer and auctoritie to be greater one, then another: for if they do, he that will ſtrive to be greateſt ſhalbe leaſt. But how is this rule of Chriſt (wherein he ſo carefully and ſo often inſtructed his Diſciples) troden vnder foo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and vtterly aboliſhed, of them that profeſſe to be his Diſciples. Not to ſpeake of the Pope, and all his con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>federates who in the hight of all iniquiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf. VVhat might wee ſay to lord Biſhops who ſo directly oppoſe Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How ſhall they be able to ſtand before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17434:32"/> lordſhipps and dignities ſo called, and ſo directly againſt his word and will. Oh that theſe thinges were not hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eies. And they that profeſſe a Prebita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, who though they beare not ſuch high names and titles as the reſt,) et by their ruleing power &amp; aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie (which by all meanes they ſeeke to enlarge) if they take not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed, their ſinne againſt this rule of Chriſt wilbe found little leſſe then anie. And if wee ſpeake ſparingly of you that profeſſe an Elderſhip thinke not you, nor lett it be thought of anie, that wee do it, either becauſe wee are partiall, or becauſe your deſerts are not fullie evill enough, for the lord knowes, &amp; wee knowe in part, and would to god you knewe your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, that your iniquitie is great herein, in your ſeeking and holding ſuperioritie over the congregations whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof you are, and that partly by auctoritie, partly by humblenes of mynd ſeekeing to beare rule over the people of god. If by this our loveing advertiſement anie of all you of whome wee have ſpoken be provoked to evill, you ſhall therein greatly increaſe your owne judgments: for the lord knowes wee ſpeake it not to provoke you to evill, but to provoke you to repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce before the great &amp; evill day come, wherein (as for all ſinne, ſo perticulerly &amp; eſpecially for this ſinne) the lord will have aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct accompt if there be not repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: wee ſay eſpecially for this ſinne, becauſe this ſinne of ſeeking ſuperioritie, rule, &amp; auctoritie hath &amp; doth vtterly deſtroy all ſincere and holy profeſſion of the goſpell, keeping in captivitie &amp; bondage the conſciences of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> overthrowing the ſtrongeſt that reſiſt, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the weake vnder foote, ſtopping vp the way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, and men hereby takeing vpon them to have in their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds onely, the keyes of the kingdome of heaven. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perticulerly vnto you to whome wee firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſpeake, take you heed, leaſt whilſt you ſet your ſelves (by your opinion) againſt Magiſtrats being of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17434:33"/> the kingdome of Chriſt, you have in the meane time, ſet vp a power and aucthoritie of your owne, and ſo your ſecond error be as evill as your firſt.</p>
               <p>To put an end to this your firſt ground, If this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample which our Saviour Chriſt bring of Kinges, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and great men, becauſe he ſaith, it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you, that is, you ſhall not be like them. It from theſe words you will yet hold, that Magiſtrats may not be of the kingdome of heaven; and of the Church, Then you muſt alſo hold (except you will ſhewe your ſelves void of all vnderſtanding) that our Saviour Chriſt in the ſame cauſe and vpon the ſame occaſion, bringing an example of a little child, and ſaieing it ſhall be ſo among you, you ſhalbe like this little child, you moſt then hold, that little children may be of the kingdome of Chriſt, and of the Church: ffor if where Chriſt ſaith. Be not like, debarr out them that are brought for the example: then where he ſaith. Be like, muſt needs admitt in them that art brought for the example. So then they that from this ground, will admitt infants in, let them ſee (if they have anie ſight) that they debarr Magiſtrats out: And you that debarr Magiſtrats out by this ground muſt admitt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in ffor they are examples of direct co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traritie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for one &amp; the ſame thinge. Therefore they that debarr out both, and they that admitt both, make thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are direct contrary to be a like, which is the moſt vniuſt and falſe vnderſtanding that can be in men. Let vs therefore the rather prevaile with you, to looke to your waies herein, and reconcile your ſelves to the word of truth. And marke well the words of our Saviour Chriſt concerning this point Mat. 18.4. who ſoever ſhall humble himſelf as this little child, the ſame is greateſt in the kingdome of heaven and vers. 3. they that are converted and become as little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17434:33"/> ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven, heere is no exception of perſons, but Kings and Princes and all great men, if they be converted and become as little children and humble them ſelves, they may enter in; and be greateſt in the kingdome of heaven, not by their princely power, but by their humilitie, which wee vnfainedly wiſh that all Kings, Princes, and Rulers would ſee, that not their greatnes, power, nor aucthoritie doth anie thinge at all advance them to, or in the kingdome of heaven: but it is their convertion and humilitie. But your opinion leads you to this; that they cannot be converted except firſt they caſt away their Magiſtracie. This is of truth your ground, a moſt woefull ground if you could ſee the footeſtepps of it, for if it be ſo that they cannot be converted except they caſt away their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie, then is their Magiſtracie ſinne, and if their magiſtracie be ſinne, then is all their adminiſtration wherein they adminiſter by power and vertue thereof ſinne, who ſhalbe able to contradict this? which way ſhall all the device of men &amp; Angells be able to avoid it, but that if Magiſtrats cannot be converted to God (that is Repent and beleeve) except they caſt away their Magiſtracie, then is their magiſtracie ſinne, for their is nothinge but ſinne that hinders faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p>Do you (that hold this fearefull opinion) yet ſee into what ſtraytes you are brought, that you have no way to turne yourſelves, if there be anie grace or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of God in you, humble your ſelves vnto the duſt before the lord and his people and proclame your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which that you may yet further be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked vnto, ſee the hight of your ſinne, ſo farr as wee in our great weakenes, are (by the mercie of god) able to ſhew you: wherein by reaſon of our ſo great weaknes, wee muſt needs exceedingly faile,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17434:34"/> and come ſhort; but yet to the vttermoſt that by the grace of god wee ſhalbe able wee will endeavour to be faithfull to god and you heerein. wee demaund cannot Magiſtrats, Repent &amp; beleeve, &amp; ſo be received or enter into the kingdome of heaven, except they caſt away their Magiſtratie? you profeſſe &amp; hold they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, why then is their Magiſtracie ſinne &amp; all that they do by the power thereof is ſinne. If this be ſo then hath the moſt holy, righteous mercifull, &amp; iuſt god, the god of all power, geven power from himſelf, &amp; appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inted an ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Magiſtracie by vertue of which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer given from god, Magiſtrats do adminiſter, and are comaunded of god to judg righteous judgment. To puniſh the wicked in juſtice, &amp; to reward or praiſe the wel doers in mercie, and all this ſay you is ſinne. And all this doth god give them power &amp; aucthoritie and comaundement to do, and in all this they are his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters doeing his will, yet not with ſtanding all this is ſinne, for if by reaſon of their Magiſtracie (retayning it) they cannot be converted, that is, Repent &amp; beleeve, then is their Magiſtracie ſinne, and then all that they do by vertue of that Magiſtracie which is ſinne, muſt needs alſo be ſinne. Hereby you charge the moſt high god to ordeyne &amp; give power from himſelf, to Magiſtrats, to ſinne &amp; ſo you make it ſinne in them to puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do evill, and to praiſe or reward the weldoers, although they do it by the power and comaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, mainteyning hereby that god gives power &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment to ſinne, what a fearefull eſtate &amp; condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this where vnto this your error hath brought you; how will they anſwere it, that have &amp; do ſo ſtiftly mainteyne &amp; teach this error, is this the leaſt comaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that they breake, &amp; teach men ſo? Mat. 5.25. To blaſpheame the name of god, in makeing him the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſinne, ſaying the holy ordinance of Magiſtracie, which he hath ordeyned is ſinne which they ſay, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17434:34"/> mainteyne that Magiſtrats may not be of the kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of heaven nor admitted of the Church, except they firſt caſt away their Magiſtracie: for there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge to be caſt away, to enter into the kingdome of heaven but ſinne, if there be no entring for Magiſtrats, but by caſting away their Magiſtracie, then muſt it needs be ſaid that Magiſtracie is ſinne. VVee go often over this point, that wee might move you with care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full adviſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es to conſider of it, which wee beſeech you by the love of god to do and not to diſhonor god and your profeſſion by ſuch errors.</p>
               <p>This which T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-appoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e writes to the Romaines. Chap. 13. and that which is ſpoken from that place, might ſuffice for this whole cauſe of Magiſtracie, for their power, auctoritie and adminiſtration, but it muſt yet be oppoſed to another ground, that is held and ſtrongly mainteyned againſt Magiſtracie, whereby the moſt ſimple harted are deceived, and that is this. The weapons of our warefare are not carnall, but mightie through god to caſt downe holds. 2. Cor. 10.4. ffrom this Scripture, divers that holds there may be ſome ſorts of Magiſtrats to end cauſes and queſtions, do yet hold that in anie caſe, they may not make warr; nor put men to death. It is to be lamented with the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, of mens ſoules to ſee the ſimple harted thus mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led, and they are deceived vnder a dangerous cullor, and great ſhewe of holines, not ſeeing the deceipt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than who transformes himſelf into an Angell of ſight herein, for what holie hart will not eaſilie be brought to thinke, that war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is an vnchriſtianlike thinge, where there is ſo much ſlaughter and blood ſhedd, and which is accompanied with ſo manie calamities and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and which is followed &amp; mainteyned by ſo great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and violence by the arme of fleſh: ſo likewiſe is it a lamentable thinge that men ſhould be executed and put to death by ſentence of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for offences. Such Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17434:35"/> you will in no caſe admitt of, wee pray you conſider, how ſhould ſuch Magiſtrats as ſome of you would allowe of, order and determyne cauſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, without the ſword of juſtice? who would obey their orders and decrees if they had no power to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine, would evill doers be perſwaded by words to do well? and would wronge doers by perſwation do right? why if they would not, then were all your Magiſtrats labor loſt, they are but weake ymagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ymagine in your mynds that there can be ſuch Magiſtrats, but let vs come to your ground. Thus ſpeakes the Appoſtle 2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. The weapons of our warfare are not carnal, the ground and cauſe of this Th-appoſtles ſpeach is this. There were certen falſe Appoſtles Chap. 11.13-20. cropt in amonge the Corintheans that made a goodly ſhewe and exalted themſelves, and had brought the people in bondage, and to vphold them ſelves in this their exaltation, they ſought to diſgrace Th-appoſtle Paul. And becauſe his writings were of great power and aucthoritie, that they could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſten the aucthoritie of them therefore they ſought to diſgrace his perſon Chap. 10. verſ. 10. his letters (ſaith one) are fore and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, but his bodilie preſence is weake and his ſpeach 1. of no value. To this Th-appoſtle anſweres verſ. 1. looke ye on thinges after the apperance? and verſ. 2. eſteeme you vs as though wee walked after the fleſh? though wee walke in the feſh, yet wee warr not after the fleſh, for the weapons of our warfare are not carnall. In all this ſhewing and teaching them that they ſhould not eſteeme of him according to the out ward apparance in the fleſh, for he came not to make a great outward boaſting ſhewe, and to ſubdue and bring men in bondage by ſuch mennes but by the power of the ſpirit, for ſaith he.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17434:35"/> The weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our warfare are not carnall: but ſaith tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ppoſtle Chap. 13.23. Seeing that ye ſeeke experience of Chriſt that ſpeaketh in me, let them knowe that have ſinned heretofore, and all others alſo that if I come, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I will not ſpare. All this &amp; much more to this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſpeakes he to the Corinthians. And to him that ſpake thoſe thinges he ſaith. Chap. 10. verſ. 11. Let ſuch on thinke, that ſuch as wee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in word by letters, when wee are abſent, ſuch alſo will wee, be indeed when wee are preſent. Thus th-appoſtle labors to ſhewe them that his miniſterie was ſpirituall, by the power whereof he came amongſt them; but ſeeing they ſought to diſgrace his miniſterie by diſgraceing his perſon, they ſhould ſee he would be the ſame in his deed preſent, that they confeſſed him to be in writing abſent: with what vnderſtanding can men gather from hence, that there may be no other weapons vſed in the world, then ſuch weapons as th-appoſtle Paul vſed heere in his miniſterie of Appoſtleſhip againſt falſe Appoſtles. wee have written thus much of this, that you might ſee how you are ſeduced, by miſapply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words of the Scripture from the ſence, which is too vſuall amongſt you.</p>
               <p>VVel, therin this place wee have learned of th-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle what were his weapons in the miniſterie of his Appoſtle ſhip, teaching the Diſciples of Chriſt to vſe onely ſuch weapons in the like miniſterie.</p>
               <p>Now let vs alſo for a full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of this point in hand be taught of the ſame Appoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> teaching by the ſame ſpirit and aucthoritie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with what weapons Magiſtrats muſt adminiſter withall in the office of their Magiſtracie. And that is ſhewed Rom. 13. where it is ſaid, they beare not the ſword for nought: for they are the miniſters of God to take v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gance on them that do evill.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17434:36"/>
               <p>Heere are the words &amp; ſence of the ſcripture goeing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; that evidently without all condiction, that God hath given Magiſtrats power from himſelf, and a ſword to puniſh and take vengance of all evill doers, for if they may take vengance of one, then of Ten, &amp; ſo of Ten thouſand: this hath god appointed, ordeyned &amp; comaunded, who is a gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious, me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cifull god, &amp; full of pittie &amp; compaſſion, yea more compaſſionate, then all men can be and therefore let not men pretend holines in this their compaſſionate and pitifull diſpoſition, that would not have Magiſtrats adminiſter with the ſword, for Sathan deceaves you thereby, and makes you more pitifull then god, &amp; therein you ſinne moſt greviou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, when you reioyce in your ſelves, and thinke you do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding well. But the thinge that mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leads you all is this becauſe you can ſee no ſworde, but the ſword of the ſpirit, and no armor but ſpirituall armor in the kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chriſt: and therefore the diſciples of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (ſay you) muſt have no other weapons, nor put on no other armor, and then can there be no putting to death, nor anie warr neither ought to be, but all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Suffer our foliſhnes if wee ſeeme as fooles to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thus vnto you. Even ſo in the kingdome of Chriſt, there is no treaſure but ſpirituall treaſure, no baggs but ſpirituall baggs Luk. 12.33. No buildings, but ſpirituall buildings. No apparell but ſpirituall apparell 1. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3. No meate but ſpirituall meate Rom. 14.17. If then you will caſt away all weapons and armor but ſuch as the diſciples of Chriſt vſe in his Kingdome, ſo muſt you alſo caſt away all your baggs and treaſure, and all your buyldings and houſes and you muſt weare no apparell, but ſpirituall apparel eate no meate but ſpirituall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. If to all this it be anſwered, that in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament the lawfull vſe of al theſe things be allowed, wee anſwere even ſo is the lawfull vſe of Magiſtracie with the ſword to puniſh evill doers allowed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17434:36"/> in the new Teſtament, as is proved from Rom. 13. which no man with anie good conſcience ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to gain ſay. To conclude wee in love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to ſee what an extreame ſtraite you are brought vnto, (wee meane all theſe that hold Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats may not be of the Church of Chriſt, and retaine their Magiſtracie) that you muſt ſay that Magiſtracie is not an holie ordinance of god, and that all that is done by the power and aucthoritie thereof is ſinne, and therefore Magiſtrats may not be admitted to be of the Church of Chriſt, except they caſt away their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie: for if you confeſſe that it is an holie ordinance of god, and that the adminiſtration and execution the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, and whatſoever is done by the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the ſame according to the word of god in the puniſhing of evil doers and praiſing &amp; rewarding the weldoers be good, and holie &amp; iuſt in the ſight of God, then may Magiſtrats be of the Church of Chriſt and retaine their Magiſtracie: for no man may be debarred out of the church of Chriſt for doeing of that which is holie and iuſt &amp; good.</p>
               <p>But to deale yet more plainely with you, that the vttermoſt depth of your error may be diſcovered, that you and all men may vtterlie deteſt and abhorr it. If you will ſay that Magiſtrats are no otherwiſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of god but as the devills are which one of our owne countrimen, the forenamed Mr. lervaſe Nevile (falling vpon this, and others your errors) moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly hath affirmed: except you will alſo hold the ſame, (which god forbid that anie child of god ſhould do) you can never deny Magiſtrats for being of the Church of Chriſt: for if you confeſſe that they are the holie and good miniſters of god applieing then ſelves there vnto, then how can you deny them as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt to be members of the Church of Chriſt, and that onely becauſe they the holie and good miniſters of god
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17434:37"/> retayne that their miniſterie office and calling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they are appointed of God.</p>
               <p>And now may you ſee that wee had iuſt cauſe in the begining of this queſtion to endeavor to ſhewe that the lord requireth a diligent, faithfull willing obedience of Magiſtrats: But the devills obey of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and againſt their will. And God doth never ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them miniſters of his mercie to anie, but wee ſee heere, God hath ordeyned Magiſtrats his miniſters for good, both in mercie and juſtice, aſwell to reward the weldoers as to puniſh the evill doers. Of all the people vpon earth none have more cauſe, to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God for this bleſſed ordinance of Magiſtracie then you, and this whole countrie and nation, in that God hath by his power and aucthoritie given vnto you magiſtrats, who have ſo defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; deliuered you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of a cruell diſtroyer &amp; will you not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding contemne this his holie ordinance, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte it as a vile thinges far be it from you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewe in this your ſo great evill.</p>
               <p>Thinke not that in the handling of this point, wee ſeeke to bring your perſons in queſtion or contempt with the higher powers, the lord knowes wee have no ſuch intent, wee knowe their worthie patience in bearing with your great weakneſſes herein, but to bring this error into contempt amonge you, that you might forſake it, that is it wee ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and that the ſimple harted might not be betrayed with it as they are, not knoweing how farr that de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pfull opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion leads them, and all vnder a ſhewe of Godlines. Much more might be ſaid then wee are able to ſay, and wee would willingly have ſaid ſomething<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this point &amp; of others, but that it is ſo difficult to get it ſett over into you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay thus much more vnto you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17434:37"/> tread vnder foote this vnholie diſpoſition that ſeemes to be ſo holie, and makes you flatters your ſelves, and thinke your ſelves moſt holie herein, and that is, in that you would not have evill doers puniſhed with the ſword. You pleaſe your ſelves much, in your pittifull diſpoſitions herein, and thinke you pleaſe God, when it is moſt evident that you ſinne greviouſly herein: for it is the good will, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and comaundement of God that evill doers ſhould be puniſhed by the ſword, and to that end he hath given power and aucthoritie to Magiſtrats, and you contrarie to the good will and pleaſure of God, would not have evill doers puniſhed with the ſword. Is not this your great ſinne to be contrarie mynded to God? take heed leaſt by this your diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you could alſo wiſh or diſire that wicked men dieing in their ſinne, might not be damned, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you ſhould wiſh the vtter diſhonor of God, for then ſhould the enimies of God triumphe over him: and then would they much God to ſcorne and have him in great deriſion: but God ſhall laugh at their diſtruction and mocke when their feare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Pro. 1.26. And all the Saincts of God ſhall reioyce with him. Reuel. 18.20. And if the Saincts in heaven reioyce and praiſe God, when he puniſheth and taketh vengance on the wicked, ought not the Saincts vpon earth to reioyce and praiſe God when they ſee or heare that the evill doers are puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed heere on earth? by ſuch power and aucthoritie as god hath appointed. And they are the more to prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe God. ſeeing the holie ghoſt doth teſtifie, that it is for their wealth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what great ſinne of ingratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and vnthankfulnes is this then in all you, that ſo diſaprove of Magiſtrats, and of their puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of evill doers by the ſword, the which Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance if it were not, all the Godlie on
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17434:38"/> earth ſhould be deſtroyed and the moſt Godly firſt. Now wee know that God is able to defend his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſword, but in that he hath appointed this holy ordinance of Magiſtracie for the preſervation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of all good men, &amp; for the ſubdueing &amp; keeping vnder and cutting of the evill doers, let none make the ſelves more wiſe and more holie then God, which you all do that diſaprove of Magiſtracie. Repent, for your ſinneing with a high hand herein, in diſhonoring God by diſaproveing his holie ordinance of Magiſtracie; which he hath comaunded ſhould be honored with all godly feare reverence and obedience. And if you will repent and truely obey god herein, then muſt you (being comaunded by the aucthoritie of the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) be ready with your owne perſons, and all that you have, to ſupport &amp; defend that ſword of juſtice which they beare and wherewith they adminiſter by that power and aucthoritie which they have from god: for who are fitter to ſupport and mainteyne the holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of god then they that profeſſe to be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of god, and who are fitter to feight iuſt and good battells then good and iuſt men; and what ſimplicitie is this to thinke, that it is more lawfull to hier men to feight a battle, then to feight it them ſelves. The people of Iſraell that were the people of god never did ſo, but they fought the battles of the lord them ſelves, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord went farth with their armies, and gave them victory over their enimies, and put their adverſaries to flight, and if magiſtracie be a holy ordinance of God now, as it was then, it is as lawfull for them to defend their countries and people as it was then, and ſo is it is lawfull for the ſervants of god, and they ought being comaunded by the magiſtrats to go to warr as well now as then: and the ſervants of god might with better conſciences and more comfort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to battle them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves (being comaunded by the higher powers that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17434:38"/> of god) although they died in battle then to hier me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſlaine for them, to whome the cauſe belonges not. There is no religion in this that magiſtrats by reaſon, of your vnwillingnes to go to battle, for the cauſe of god and for your owne ſafeties &amp; preſervation ſhould be forced to hier men to feight for you (although you pay for it) and in all this you pretend Religion and conſcience: but it is evident by the word of god, that if magiſtracie be a holie ordinance of god, it is to be ſupported by all holy and good men, and meanes: And if it be not a holy Ordinance of god, then are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats but the miniſters of god as the devills are: then are they not to be obeyed for conſcience ſake, not to be honored: for wee are not bound of conſcience to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and obey the power, aucthoritie, and miniſtery of devills, but to reſiſt it: and ſo Th-appoſtle Pauls doctrine Rom. 13. and Th-appoſtle Peters doctrine. 1. Pet. 2.3.17. Is all made falſe and erronious. But far be it from anie that have anie touch of true godlines, to deny that holy ordinance of magiſtracie, and ſo to overthrowe the holy doctrines of Th-appoſtles. Let the godly bewarr of ſuch. Th-appoſtle Peter hath foretold of them, and of their manner of proceding, for.</p>
               <p>Firſt he ſheweth that there ſhalbe falſe teachers, which privilie ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the lord that hath bought them, and by their followers the way of truth ſhalbe evill ſpoken of. And theſe are they which ſhall diſpiſe gouerment; which are bould, and ſtand in their owne conceipt, and feare not to ſpeake evill of them that are in dignitie 2. Pet. 2.1-10. let vs applie this to the perſons and cauſe in hand: Theſe men that moſt ſtifely ſtand againſt magiſtracie, have they not brought in damnable hereſies? do they not deny the lord that hath bought them? are not the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe they that deny the true humanitie of Chriſt, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17434:39"/> him to have had a true earthly naturall bodie, wherewith he bought them: which they that deny or are ignorant of, that he had a true naturall earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodie, they deny, and are ignorant that the lord hath bought them. VVee will not now ſpeake to the reſt of their damnable hereſies: but to come to this which is one of them, they diſpiſe goverment, and ſpeake evill of them that are in dignitie. Can there be greater diſpiſers of goverment then they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be lawfull to puniſh evill doers with the ſword, for take away the ſword and where is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment, will evill doers be governed with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of reed? do wee not ſee daylie that manie feares not the ſword? and if the ſword of juſtice were taken away, all goverment were overthrowne, and can there be greater diſpiſers of goverment, then they that would altogether over throwe it. And they ſpeake evill of them that are in dignitie and aucthoritie. Do not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe men ſpeake evill of them when then teach and condemne them for evill doers in their execution of juſtice againſt offenders? and can they ſpeake grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evill then to ſay, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> evill doers as are not worthie to be members of the Church of Chriſt? what greater evill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tempt can be caſt vpon them, both before God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hereby they are abſolutely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be the miniſters of god, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the devills are. Can there greater evill be ſpoken then this. To make it more plaine, that you which touch theſe thinges againſt Magiſtracy are theſe falſe The achers that the Appoſtle Peter heere ſpeaketh of. This is one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peciall ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, that you do it privilie, for can falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> teach more privilie then you that teach this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you do not vnderſtand teaching privily to be in corners and privie places. Th appoſtle ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> meaning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for he ſpeakes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17434:39"/> of bringing in hereſies privily in teaching of doctrine; and is not this hereſie againſt Magiſtrats moſt privily brought in vnder a culler? from our Saviour Chriſts owne words where he ſaith. It ſhall not be ſo among you: And from Th-appoſtles words. The weapons of our warfare are not carnall. Is it not privily done? to wreſt the ſcriptures ſo deceitfully from a ſhewe of words leaving the true ſence of the place, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by concluding moſt privilie and deceitfully, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats bearing the ſword may not be of the kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chriſt not of his Church. but let that ſuffice which is ſpoken before of the miſvnderſtanding of theſe Scriptures. And ſee further, how vnder this firſt damnable hereſie of denying Magiſtrats to be of the Church, moſt privily is this hereſie brought in that Magiſtracie is vtterly vnlawfull, and all that is done by the power and aucthoritie thereof is ſinne; for as wee have ſhewed there is nothinge but ſinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barrs anie from being members of Chriſts Church, they then that hold that Magiſtracie debarrs men from being members of Chriſts Church muſt needs hold that Magiſtracie is ſinne: and that Magiſtrats by reaſon of their office and aucthoritie are ſinners. For although a Magiſtrat ſhould manifeſt never ſo great faith and repentance, yet theſe men will not yeild that he may be of the Church of Chriſt: for except be caſt away his Magiſtracie, his ſaith and repentance is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge. This vnholy Office &amp; vnſanctified and horitie doth vtterly overthrowe faith and repentance. Let it not diſpleaſe you that wee write thus plainely: ſet if it be a holie Office, and Sanctified aucthoritie, then it cannot debarr anie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being members of the church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus may you, &amp; all ſee, that theſe among you which teach that Magiſtrats may not be of the Church,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17434:40"/> And that it is not lawfull for them to puniſh evill doers with the ſword, nor by the ſword to mainteyne warr for the preſervation of their contries &amp; people, theſe are they that privily bring in damnable hereſies, deſpiſing goverment and ſpeaking evill of theſe that are in dignitie and aucthoritie, in that hereby they ſeeke the vtter overthrowe of all goverment, and acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pt aucthoritie and magiſtracie moſt viſe, becauſe evill doers are puniſhed thereby, which you teach ought not to be, but is ſinne &amp; wickednes to be done. And if all men in theſe Provinces vnder the goverment of the lords &amp; ſtats generall were of your mynds, as you would have them, where were goverment and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats? were it not all in the duſt? Thus is it evident that you would have Kings, Princes, &amp; magiſtrats vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed. Is not this hereſie privily brought in: vnder ſo great a ſhewe of godlines to deſtroy the holy ordinance of god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how manie of you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that this hereſie leads you to accompt magiſtrats the miniſters of god, but as the devills are? wee hope there are tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſands of you that have no ſuch thoughs, and yet it is moſt evident, and cannot be avoyded but it is, the end of your ground &amp; rule, is not this privily brought in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e not therefore deceived by f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeaches, for weep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feſte vnto you, that it by this that is already ſaid it do not plainely appeare to anie indifferent reader that your ground leads you to this, that all that magiſtrats do, (by vertue and power of their Office in puniſhing evill doers) is ſinne in them; if anie thinke good to oppoſe wee wil by gods aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce make it moſt clere, that all may ſee it that wincke not with their eies. If therefore you like not to hold that magiſtrats are no otherwiſe the miniſters of god, but as the devils are, then leave of alſo to hold that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats by reaſon of their magiſtracie are to be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the kingdome of Church of Chriſt. And
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17434:40"/> alſo it ſhall appeare, that this your ground doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently overthrowe all Magiſtracie in the whole earth: for if God would have all Kings &amp; Princes ſaved, and come to the knowledg &amp; profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his truth, which Th-appoſtle ſaith he would 1. Tim. 2.2.4. and you confeſſe the ſame, and if they cannot come to the knowledg and profeſſion of the truth except they caſt away their Magiſtracie (as you ſay and hold) then muſt all Magiſtracie be caſt away in the whole world; for God would have all the Kings Princes, and Magiſtrats vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth to come to the knowledg of the truth &amp; be ſaved. And if you like not to overthrowe all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats and Magiſtracie in the earth, then leave of to hold that they may not be of the kingdome &amp; church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>One other marke that ſhewes you are the falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers Th-appoſtle ſpeakes of, is, that you ſtand in your owne conceite, this wee have found in ſome of you, and wee require wee may not now find it in you all for then ſhall it appeare evidently vnto all men.</p>
               <p>Thus have wee in theſe pointes wherein wee differ from you, ſpoken ſo farr as God hath enabled vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you all with ſinglenes of hart to try your ſtanding in theſe thinges wee have ſpoken of, and that you would not hold theſe opinions, becauſe you have held them long, but that you will loveingly be adviſed to ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee whether you have any Good warrant thus to hold and profeſſe and teach men ſo. Approve your ſelves now vnto vs, and vnto all men, that you walke not blindly in the ſtepps of them that have gone before you, but that you diſire and endeavor to walke by true ſanctified knowledg from the Scriptures, and that you do not ſo much ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to heape multitudes together, and build vp great Churches and congregations; as to gather together a holy people, and biuld vp pure Churches in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17434:41"/> of the true faith, that you may be approved of God, which neither you nor anie people can ever do, except you firſt make ſure, that your doctrine be pure and vndefiled: for though a people ſhould never ſo much excell in all holines of converſation, yea though they ſhould excell in works, in love, &amp; ſervice, in faith &amp; patience, &amp; that their workes ſhould be more at laſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at firſt Reuel. 2.19. yet if they ſuffer falſe doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; falſe teachers, they are impure &amp; polluted churches for a little leave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaveneth the whole lumpe Gal 5.9. &amp; the lord will not approve of them, but will certenly come againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſword of his mouth, &amp; will re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>move their candle ſuckes out of there places.</p>
               <p>This the Lord ſaith, but who beleeves the word of the lord herein. If Churches and Congregations did beleeve theſe words of the lord, it would make them try their doctrines by the word of the lord &amp; go vpon ſound grounds with knowledg &amp; vnderſtanding from the word of truth, being teſtified vnto them by the teaching of the ſpirit of God, and not receive doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vpon the good opinion they have of their Teachers knowledg, holines &amp; faithfulnes, although they ſhould excell in all theſe thinges: neither would the people of God be carried away after anie doctrines by the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge working affections of their mynds, judging it to be the working of the ſpirit of God, when it is nothinge but the ſpirit of their owne affections, wherein they may have great motions and feelings with much zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le but not according to knowledg. Rom. 10.2. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are wee comaunded not to beleeve every ſpirit, neither in our ſelves nor in others: but to try firſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God. And hereby ſhall wee knowe the ſpirit of error. If wee heare Gods wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d 1. Ioh. 4.6. That is, if wee ſearch and try everie thinge thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Churches and congregations would thus
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17434:41"/> looke vnto their waies, and not hold errors for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie ſake, nor walke in by pathes by affections. It is better to hold the truth alone, &amp; to walke in the waies thereof, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary to all the affections of the hart, which is deceitfull: but this is a hard doctrine, who is able to hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it. It is a pleaſing thinge to walke in a profeſſion of Religion with a multitude, and eſpecially it but ſome of the grounds of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith agree with mens mynds. This overthrowes the firſt beginings of the Religion of God when men will chuſe to walke with that people, and in that profeſſion of faith that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt pleaſeth their mynds, not ſo much regarding the truth of their faith nor the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy walkeing therein: although they may miſlike ſome thinges yet if ſome pleaſe them well, they will not differ for ſmake matters: and when they are once gathered and kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t together in a multitude, then though error after error be diſcovered and ſinne after ſinne comitted, there may be no breaking vpon anie conditions. And this overthrowes all growth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. VVee wiſh you and all great congregations to looke to your ſelves, that you be not more carefull to mainteyne your multitude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lords truth. It is not a multitude in error &amp; ſinne, that can pleaſe God: Noe, a fewe walking together in the truth with holines ſhalbe acceptable in his ſight, if they be but two or three, he will be in the midſt of them. Therefore pleaſe not your ſelves in your multitudes, walking in ſo manie errors as you do: for if you repent not of theſe whereof wee have made mention, and of all other your errors and falſe doctrins mainteyned amongſt you, the lord will aſſuredly make you deſolate: for thus hath he threatned, and executed his judgment vpon Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus and Thyatira becauſe they repented not and he threatnes and will execute the ſame judgment vpon you which ſinne after the like manner of tranſgreſſion, of you repent not. And your gifts and grates being
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17434:42"/> manie leſſe then the gifts and graces of thoſe Churches and your falſe doctrines and ſinnes already manie moe, the greater, and more ſpedily will his jugdments be vpon you, if you repent not, which wee vnfainedly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the lord to give you Grace to do; Be warned you that are leaders, whilſt it is to day, &amp; harden not your harts: why ſhould you periſh in your ſinnes? &amp; lead ſo manie ſimples ſoule to deſtruction with you.</p>
               <p>Thus praying all the gratious harted amongſt you, to remember that the wiſe man ſaith. Open rebuke is better then ſecreet love, and the wounds of a lover are faithfull Pro. 27.5.6. And wee will hope that though wee reprove you, wee ſhall at length find more love (which is all wee require of you) then they that ſo flatter you with their tougnes. The grace of our lord Ieſus Chriſt, be with you Amen.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Cant. 4.8.</bibl>
                     <p>COme from Lebanon, even come from Lebanon, and looke from the topp of Amanah, from the topp of Shenir and Hermon, from the Denns of the Lyons, and from the mountayns of the Leopards.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:17434:42"/>
            <head>To all the moſt vvorthy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Learned Teachers, and Godly people of all eſtats and conditions in theſe vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. Grace and peace from God the father, and our lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>VVEE, amonge the reſt of the people of God, that profeſſe the goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, have great cauſe to praiſe the lord for the freedome &amp; libertie that wee have in theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to profeſſe &amp; ſpeake in the name of Ieſus: and wee are bound, and do with all humblenes of hart thankfullie acknowledg it. And wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the lord in mercie to recompence it ſeaven-fold into the boſome of thoſe that are in auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by whoſe great fauour wee enioy this bleſſed and comfortable libertie: the which libertie wee have not the leaſt thouhts to abuſe neither by the grace and mercie of God will ever willingly do. And wee humblie crave now, that wee may with favour and good acceptance vſe this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libertie thus fair as to propound the ground of Religion by way of queſtion and demaund, &amp; wee doubt not (through the grace of God) but it being throughly and faithfullie debated and tryed by the Godly, wiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e learned, it will put a ſhort end to that longe continewed controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Gods eternall decree of life and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and condemnation, And thus with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and due reſpect vnto all deg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ees of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17434:43"/> wee proceed.</p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>Our firſt queſtion and demaund is.</head>
               <p n="1">1. VVether God decreed not, that if Adam did obey, he ſhould live?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>Our ſecond.</head>
               <p n="2">2. VVhether God did not, according to this his decree, create Adam in his owne jmage Gen. 1.17. In righteouſnes, &amp; true holines Ephe. 4.24. gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing him thereby free will &amp; power, in, and of himſelf, that he might obey &amp; live?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>Our third.</head>
               <p n="3">3. VVhether God did not according to this his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rke of creation give Adam his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> obey, &amp; live. Gen. 2.16.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>Our fovvrth.</head>
               <p n="4">4. God then decreeing that if Adam did obey he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> live and giveing him freewil &amp; power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; of himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lf that he might obey &amp; live, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to they &amp; live. Our demaund <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nderſtanding it can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that God decreed Adam ſhould diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were not this to make God in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worke, &amp; in his comaundment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17434:43"/> to himſelf? doth God decree that if Adam did obey he ſhould live, &amp; decree that he ſhould diſobey &amp; dye? doth God create Adam after his owne jmage, with power &amp; will to worke righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, &amp; decree that he ſhould worke vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes &amp; ſinne doth God comaund Adam to obey, &amp; decree he ſhould diſobey wee demaund how theſe thinges can agree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>Our fift.</head>
               <p n="5">5. VVhether God ever made anie other decree with man-kind concerming life &amp; death ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; condemnation but that he made with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam? Then God not decreing Adam to ſinne by whome ſinne entred Rom. 5 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Nor Adam to be condemned, by whoſe ſinne, condemnaton came on all men Rom. 5.18. hovv can it be ſaid, that God hath decreed anie man to ſinne: or anie man to condemnation?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>Our Sixt.</head>
               <p n="6">6. VVhether Gods decree vvas, not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before all beginings. That if Adam deſobeyed &amp; ſinned he ſhould dye? Gen. 2.17. hovv then is it ſaid, that it vvas Gods decree that he ſhould diſobey &amp; dye? both theſe cannot ſtand: &amp; can the firſt be denyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:17434:44"/>
               <head>Our Seaventh.</head>
               <p n="7">7. If anie ſhould through vnadviſednes not knovving God, or of vvilfull vvickednes, deny Adam before his fall to have freevvill &amp; povver to vvorke righteouſnes: vvee demaund of them vvas not his vnderſtanding holy? his vvill holy? and all the faculties &amp; povvers of his ſoule &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die holy? &amp; had he not povver to vſe them holily? If all theſe thinges vvere not ſo, hovv is that true vvhich God hath ſaid. In the jmage of God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he him?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <head>Our Eight.</head>
               <p n="8">8. VVhether Adam before his fall did not vſe all the faculties &amp; povvers of his ſoule &amp; body vvholy to Gods glory? vvhen the lord brought vnto him all the foule of heaven &amp; every beaſt of the feild, to ſee hovv he vvould call them, and he gave names vnto all cattle, &amp; to the foules of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp; to every beaſt of the feild: as alſo vvhen the lord brought the vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had made, to Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Adam ſaid, this novv is bone of my bone &amp; fleſh of my fleſh, ſhe ſhalbe called vvoman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe vvas taken out of man. VVee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, vvhether it be not heare moſt evident &amp; plaine, that Adam had free povver over his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding vvill, &amp; affections, vvhen he did the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thinges to the glory of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:17434:44"/>
               <head>Our Nynth.</head>
               <p n="9">9, Adam haveing then freevvill &amp; povver from God in, &amp; by his creation to obey &amp; live, hovv can it poſſibly be ſaid that God in his eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree decreed him or anie man to condemnation?</p>
               <p>VVee diſire a Godly carefull conſideration &amp; reveivving of theſe things, for vpon this ground depends the vvhole cauſe of Predeſtination and gods decree co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for if Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had freevvil &amp; povver to obey, vvhich never ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that knevve God yet denyed, then hovv could God decree anie man to condemnation? and if Adam had not freevvill and povver to obey, then God decreed he ſhould diſobey &amp; ſinne, &amp; then hovv can it be denyed but God hath decreed men to condemnation, &amp; ſo is vniuerſall redemption vtterly overthrovvne: for hovv could Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deame all, &amp; God decree ſome to be condemned: But if Adam had freevvill and povver to obey, then God decreed no man to condemnation: and if God decreed no man to condemnation before the begining of the vvorld, then the lambe ſlayne from before the begining of the vvorld, muſt needs be given a Redeamer for all men. And then are all men bound to glorifie God in that he hath given a Saviour and meanes of ſalvation for them. But if he be not given a ſaviour for all men, then the greateſt part of men in the vvorld, have no cauſe to glorifie God therein. And vvee demaund vvhether this be not greatly to rob god of his honor herein.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:17434:45"/>
               <p>And let vs yet requier one thinge more at your hands that baptize infants: vvhether you do not of faith, baptiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as being redeamed by Chriſt in that you declare them (as appeareth in your forme of baptiſme) to be ſanctified in Chriſt and therefore that they ought to be Baptized, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, vvhich is the bodie of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Surely it cannot be but that you faithfullie belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve that all the infants you Baptiſe are redeamed by Chriſt or els you vvould not Baptiſe them into the name of Chriſt, &amp; acknovvledg the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> members of his bodie. And if you do hold, all the infants you Baptiſe to bereadeamed by Chriſt, then if your rule of perticuler Redemption &amp; perticuler Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, be a true rule, you muſt needs hold that all Dutch-land muſt be ſaved, and no one of them can be condemned: and ſo muſt you hold the like of all England, all France, all Scotland and generally of all the Nations vvhoſe Baptiſing of infants you approve of. And in that you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Baptiſing of all the Turkes, and all the Heathens vvhat ſoever &amp; their infants, if they ſhould come vnto the acknovvledging of the faith of Ieſus Chriſt vvhich vvee hope none can ſay, but they may, do you not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> plaine ſhevve that you ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Chriſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo: &amp; thus you hold that Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt hath Rede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all the vvorld, if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yourſelves in your ovvne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vvee beſeech you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> on be able (through Go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:17434:45"/> of your faith herein.</p>
               <p>Oh that wee might on Chriſts be half require you with Godly carefull adviſednes throughly to conſider of theſe few thinges ſo ſimplie and plainely ſet downe. That al the honor and praiſe that is due vnto Chriſt for that his great worke of Redemption might freely be given vnto him: and that none that profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e would ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve to leſſen his vnſpeakeable worke of mercie herein, whereby they do not onely leſſen the honor and praiſe due vnto him for that his ſo gracious worke of redeaming all without reſpect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but they do alſo depri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnderſtanding of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto all, being all but vnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in Adam by whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> condemnation went over all, the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt was for given Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then muſt it needs be forgiven to all his poſteritie, ſeeing God doth nor puniſh the Child for the fathers ſinne, eſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ially forgiveing the father that ſinne. Let men be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re how they take from the word of God and ſo flee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vengeance that is to come vpon all thoſe that ſhall ſo do.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Grace be vvith you</salute> Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd whereas it is ſuſpected that they which hold vniuerſal Redemption do, or muſt hold freewill, wee deſire to teſtifie vnto all, for the cleering of our ſelves from the ſuſpect of that moſt damnable hereſie, that god in mercie hath thus farr given vs grace to ſee That who ſoever holds vniuerſall red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ption by Chriſt, they cannot hold frewill, if they have anie vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: ffor freewill d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th vtterly aboliſh Chriſt, and deſtroy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> workes: for freewill is to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve abſolute power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mans ſelf to worke righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17434:46"/> and obey god in perfect obedience; And ſuch men need no Chriſt, and if anie ſhalbe ſo blind as to thinke that Chriſt reſtored man into his former eſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt there needs be a new tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of good, and evill: for there is no other way ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the Scriptures, for a perfect man that is reſtored to Adams eſtate, to ſinne, but by eating of that tree, and if man be reſtored to perfection: or if all men fell not in Adam, as the ſcriptures teſtifie they did. Rom. 5.12.18. then man hath power in himſelf to obey, and then ſome may yet obey, and ſo ſtand no need of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>VVe knowe not anie certentie of theſe mens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, therefore wee will not enter into them, onely one man once told vs he had freewill, but wee found him to hold ſo manie other horrible opinions wherein he was ſo obſtinate as wee had no faith no have anie further conference with him. To theſe men onely thus much do wee ſay, that thus ſpeaketh the word of god Gen. 5.2. God created Adam, in the likenes of god made he him, and verſ. 3. Adam lived an hundreth and thirtie yeres, and begat a child in his owne likenes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his jmage. If me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cannot ſee heare that Adam begat not a could in the likenes of god, but in his owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and that the likenes or jmage of god, which is Perfection, righteouſnes, and true holines, doth differ, and is cleane contrary to the likenes and jmage of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Adam, who when he began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heth his ſonne was of himſelf an imperfect, vnholy, vnrighteous man. If they cannot ſee this, then are they void of all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of god And thus much wee leave for a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to all thoſe that ſtand for freewill, that they may looke backe in whoſe jmage and likenes they are begotten and if their fathers begatt them in the jmage of God, then are they certenly perfect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and ſo have freewill: but if then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> begatt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17434:46"/> them, in their owne jmage and likenes, as Adam begatt Sheth his ſonne, then let them with David cry out and confeſſe. Behold I was borne in iniquitie and in ſinne hath my mother conceived me. Pſal. 51.5. And if they confeſſe that they were borne in iniquitie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in ſinne as the holie man David was, how doth the devill bewitch them to make them thinke, that they are perfect and have freewill.</p>
               <p>For our ſelves wee confeſſe with. Th-appoſtle Rom. 7.18. wee knowe that mvs that is in our fleſh dwelleth no good thinge. And Chriſt hath taught vs Io. 3.6. That which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh, and therefore muſt needs onely do the workes of the fleſh: &amp; that which is borne of the ſpirit is ſpirit, and therefore all that are borne of the fleſh muſt be borne againe, before they can be ſpirituall. And wee confeſſe with the ſame Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle 1. Cor. 1.30. That wee are of God onely in Chriſt Ieſus, who of god is made vnto vs, wiſedome and righteouſnes and ſanctification and redemption. &amp; Eph. 2.8.9. By grace onely are wee ſaved through faith, and that not of our ſelves but of the gift of god not of workes. Let it heere be obſerved that faith is a Created quallitie in man, as knowledg is, which being ſanctified by the ſpirit of grace, is knowledg to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and faith to ſalvations: And therefore our ſaviour Chriſt ſheweing that knowledg is not ſufficient ſaith. Not the knowers of my will but the doers are juſtified. And the holy ghoſt (ſpeakeing of faith) ſaith. Faith without works is dead, ſheweing that the devills be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve Iam. 2. And therefore faith is not a new gift, but it is Grace in Chriſt which Th-appoſtle ſaith in this place, is the gift of God whereby mens knowledg and faith are ſanctified to ſalvation, and ſo are ſaved by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce onely, through faith ſanctified by that grace of god in Chriſt. And this grace of god, which is his mercie by Chriſt, hath god given to all: ffor that grace of
<pb facs="tcp:17434:47"/> God that bringeth ſalvation vnto all men hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Tit. 2.10. but all receive it not, as Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas teſtifie againſt the Iewes Act. 13.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Yee put from you the word of God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yourſelves vnworthy of everlaſting life. And Stephen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ith to them Act. 7.51. Yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the holy ghoſt. Now wee pray that the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of ſuch as, by the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> carried into theſe errors before ſpoken of, and wee knowe not into how manie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grevious &amp; damnable, may not be a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block to hinder a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e gracious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>att from ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſeekeing after &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>raccing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of god they hold. Let the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed truth of god be never the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e beloved &amp; liked of, becauſe manie that pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it hold fearefull errors, but rather embrace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and vſe all godly diligence to bring them out of their errors, if it be poſſible, leaſt they periſh in them, which is greath to be feared in manie of them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Helvvys</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17434:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17434:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17434:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17434:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17434:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17434:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17434:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17434:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17434:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17434:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17434:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17434:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17434:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17434:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17434:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17434:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17434:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17434:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17434:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17434:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17434:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17434:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17434:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17434:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17434:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17434:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17434:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17434:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17434:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17434:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17434:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17434:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17434:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17434:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:17434:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17434:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17434:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17434:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17434:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17434:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17434:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17434:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17434:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17434:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17434:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17434:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:17434:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:17434:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17434:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:17434:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:17434:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:17434:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:17434:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:17434:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:17434:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:17434:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:17434:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:17434:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:17434:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:17434:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:17434:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:17434:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:17434:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:17434:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:17434:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:17434:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:95"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17434:95"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
